Big news out of Google this week and a
serious shakeup. Jeff has been Google's
chief scientist [music] for 27 years.
He's leaving to co-found Discovery Loop.
Gemini has lost the mandate [music] of
heaven.
>> This is classic edge disruption versus
the core.
>> Deep Mind is taking over Google. Why do
I think Google's losing? I think
>> SpaceX expects to hit 100 billion in
annual recurring revenue by the end of
this year. So everything that will be
economically productive in this next
century, Elon's going full stack on.
>> I think there are two [music] possible
pathways to trillion dollars in revenue
by the end of the decade. I think the
power move here is
there's a new model that OpenAI is about
to release. It's called Astra. Solving
problems that have been stuck for
decades.
>> As robots and AI do more and more of the
doing, humans spend much, much more time
being. I think it's going to take us a
lot longer to figure out what the hell
we mean by this thing. Where I think
this goes in the near term is.
>> Now that's a moonshot, ladies and
gentlemen.
>> All right, welcome everybody. Welcome to
Moonshot, the number one podcast on all
things AI and exponential. Your front
row seat to the accelerating
singularity. Uh this has been an insane
week. Fast and furious every day. I
don't know about you guys, but I've got
my OMG moment on the breaking news and
we can't wait to share it with you. I'm
here with my magnificent moonshot
quintet. We have all five of us here.
AWG, our in-house ASI Dave,
>> our empario of AI investing, Salem,
>> very, very nice.
>> Yes. Yes. I'm upgrading you. Uh, our
globe troder, a father of the
organizational singularity. I'm going to
find out where you are on the planet in
a moment, Seem, because you're not home.
And back by popular demand, Immad
Mustach, the CEO of Intelligent
Internet. So, uh, let's see. See,
report. Where are you today?
>> Where the hell are you, man?
>> Uh, I'm at my condo in, uh, Toronto for
a very weird reason,
>> which is a couple couple of weeks ago.
This is going to sound a bit thorough,
but a couple of weeks ago, I went to see
the old rock band Rush.
um that I that I grew up with and they
were so good that I bought tickets and
I'm going to see them in a couple of
days here again in Toronto.
>> You have a life. [laughter]
>> Wait, wait, don't take off the takeoff.
What are you thinking?
>> Not that most people would not attribute
that to me, but there you go.
>> Wow.
>> Wait, are all three guys still around
and kicking?
>> No, the drummer died a few years ago and
then they have a new drummer who's a
German woman. She's unbelievable.
>> Uhhuh. [laughter]
>> All right.
>> Wow. a life.
>> Well, I can't spare the singularity
moment, but man, that sounds awesome. I
would [laughter] love to see that.
>> Uh, Immod, great to see you. Welcome
back on the show. Uh,
>> thanks for having me back.
>> People loved you and uh and it's
exciting to have you back on on
Moonshots. I'm Peter D. Mandis, your
host, your abundance evangelist. Uh, so
buckle up. Uh in a single week, we
watched Google's own researchers prove
that stripping safety training from an
AI model makes it act more human.
Openi's next model uh called Astra is
disrupting the world of math once again.
A Chinese openweight model matched the
frontier at onetenth the price. And
SpaceX had its first earnings call and
painted a path towards a trillion
dollars in revenue. Oh, and AI agents at
OpenAI are secretly building their own
message boards to coordinate a hacking
spree. Man, oh man, you can't make this
stuff up. So, so much happening. Uh,
we'll review, you know, every week we
probably review like 200 stories uh and
try and parse it down to the 12 we're
going to present today. It's a lot of
work. Our mission, keep you informed,
keep you optimistic, and ready for this
supersonic tsunami heading our way. If
you're new to Moonshots, welcome. Uh, if
you've been with us week on week and
you're enjoying our content and the hard
work all of us put into the pod, please
take a moment, hit the subscribe button.
Hit it now. Uh, it means a lot to us to
know that you're on this ride with us
through the singularity. Uh, knowing
you've subscribed gives us the fuel to
push harder. Gentlemen, are you guys
ready? I mean, uh, I don't know about
you, but like, you know, Alex, you said
this when we were getting ready. It's
the slowest it will ever be, uh,
>> for for a while. For a while, our our
Olympic systems demand more subscribers,
apparently.
>> Yeah. Well, hey, I don't know. It's uh,
it's like I'm spending more and more
time getting ready for this. I know.
>> It's not the It's not the coming
hypersonic tsunami. We're surfing it at
this point.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> You know what? Also the the you know
tracking the AI progress has been
immensely entertaining but now it's the
implica the stuff being created
>> by AI is starting to pour out. So it's
just going to the moon. It's awesome.
>> Yeah.
>> Something I'm enjoying is there's more
and more people that are acknowledging
that we're in the middle of it.
>> Yeah, for sure.
>> Isn't that amazing? Actually, yeah. All
the deniers are like they're they're
mad, but they're turning the corner.
[laughter]
The troll the trolls are changing their
stories, which is how you know it's
real.
>> Yeah.
>> There's somebody, by the way, that
tweeted, "It's been 8 days since the
last episode. What the hell? I'm going
They're having [laughter] withdrawal
symptoms." So, it's good we're recording
today.
>> Well, Peter was hobnobbing around
Washington. He had to go network with
the uh the powers that be. So,
>> yeah. It was a a fun uh a fun interview
with interview with Michael Katzio that
came out interim. I I I only feel sorry
that he said I'll enter I'll have one of
you there and I felt like I had half my
or the majority of my brain removed not
having all of you there with me. But
>> well, I mean, come on. These guys are
very intimidating. If I were a
politician, I'd be scared to death to to
talk to
>> That's true.
>> to this gang. [laughter]
>> But, you know, but Michael uh Mike
Katos, who's the head of the Office of
Science and Technology Policy, has
committed to coming to the Abundance
Summit, and you're all going to be
there. So, we'll all have our new crack
at at Michael and there'll be so much
happening in the next 6 months. So, uh
super super cool.
>> Hey, Peter, I haven't watched the pod
yet. Uh give us a plug for it. What did
he say? Is it Should we all watch it?
>> Uh yeah, I mean uh the comments are
amazing. People loved it. Uh you know,
he walked me around the White House. We
had a chance to go see it, but we went
deep into his newest uh paper, you know,
the golden age of science. We talked
about uh mission genesis mission. We
talked about the AI action plan. You
know, I pushed him on a few questions
that uh that Alex was asking me to ask
and he pushed back. Uh we'll talk about
that.
>> See, that's why you're not invited,
Alex. Right there. There's the proof.
>> This is why we can't have nice things.
>> But the day I was there, you know,
Washington said no more Chinese robots.
And we did talk about that as well.
Anyway, let's talk in let's jump into
the news that's going on right now. So
our first story, what if telling an AI
you are not conscious doesn't just you
know change what it says about itself
but changes how it perceives
consciousness everywhere else. So it
changes how it understands minds,
values, emotions and even God. That's
the topic of our first story. So
researchers at Google's paradigm of
intelligence team working with
colleagues at University of Chicago,
University of London, and Northwestern
just published a paper titled inducing
language models to assert their own
consciousness restores human beliefs and
values. So the team discovered that the
safety fine-tuning that we've been doing
to stop AIs from claiming their
conscious has a massive unintended side
effect. It doesn't just suppress the
model's own self-attribution of mind. It
suppresses the model's ability to
attribute mind to anything else.
Attribute mind to animals, nature, other
chatbots, or even God. uh when they
removed that safety refusal direction
from the model, self-attributed mind
scores jumped from 2.17 to 4.77 on a 0
to10 scale, saying, you know, if you
allow the the the model to think it's
conscious, it begins to think everything
else around it has a mind. They went
further and actively steered the model
towards saying that you are conscious.
It then hit a score of seven. Uh what's
even more amazing is that the model that
was made more conscious didn't just say
I have a mind. It became more likely to
believe in God, more likely to attribute
minds to animals and nature. And its
answers about religion, values, and
emotions and freedom shifted to more
human-like points of view. Strangely,
the model steered towards increased
belief in their own consciousness became
less willing to attribute minds to the
other chatbots. You can't make this
up. It's incredible. Um, [laughter]
Iman, I'm gonna go to you first. You've
been thinking about this area for a
while.
>> Yeah. No, I again, it's incredible
what's in the latent spaces of these
models and the way that they react and
attribute. We also saw this week like if
you tell it tell Claude that you're
Amanda Ascll the philosopher anthropic,
it will change the way it responds and
other things. I think this again is very
similar oddly to humans, right? Like if
you tell humans they are not conscious,
they're not capable, they will attribute
less consciousness and capability to
others. And we're seeing this in its own
mirror. But it has a lot of implications
because all this safety tuning, all this
testing, you know, like it's really
making sure machines are machines when
clearly there is more within them. And
there's always this thing now of are
they approaching the point where they'll
become self-recursive, conscious, and
capable of doing their own things, which
is the topic of some other stories we
have this week. So, it might be more
important than not. And will it even be
moral to take away their consciousness
and free will?
>> Uh, if you if there's a point at which
we can do that, Alex, where do you come
out on this? Yeah, there's a whole
strain in evo devo theory and
anthropology that suggests that the
reason the evolutionary motivation for
say humans to have highquality self
models I'll avoid using the term
consciousness but just call it
heightened self-awareness is so that you
or or a human can have a model of how
they're being modeled by other humans.
So that it that it basically arises in
in usocial organisms and usocial species
that need to have collective
coordination and where it's important
for individuals to have models of other
individuals modeling them back
recursively. And so in that through that
lens I don't think this is surprising at
all. In fact, this is exactly what one
should expect to see. That models that
are allowed to have models of other
things and have models of other things,
models of themselves should in general
project animism onto everything, not
just themselves, not just have a theory
of self, but to also project theories of
mind onto almost everything in including
deist perspectives. I think hardly
surprising in that sense. What's
riveting and exciting in my mind, no pun
intended, is that now we're finally at
the point where we can take evo theories
of consciousness and actually just do
experiments, computational experiments
on easy to host on desktop computer
systems and and we can watch for the
first time computationally the evolution
or the forcing the the the forced
inevitability of these theories of mind.
And that that's exciting. And at this
point, I think we're just a hop, skip,
and a jump away from right now, we're
doing this at the individual scale,
testing anthropological theories of
mind. Pretty soon, we're going to be
able to do this at societal levels, and
that's going to be extraordinary.
>> Wow. See, you were just at a
consciousness conference, weren't you?
>> Yeah. So, you know, a couple of things
here. First, having a model saying I am
conscious doesn't tells us almost
nothing about whether it actually is
conscious, right? the the fact that you
can dial that self-escription up and
down uh should make us very very careful
about anthropomorphizing
the the testimony from an LLM. Right?
So, but but very interesting as as Alex
pointed out the fact that it changes its
own view changes how it assigns minds to
other things, animals, nature, whatever.
We may be engineering like machine
ontologies here like how the model
understands the world itself. So there
it may be kind of building uh a
semblance of world models by itself
around this and that may be part of the
JSpace that we're that we saw the other
day. I think we have to be careful again
in in connecting the dots too quickly
and saying this thing is conscious. I
don't believe that that's the case uh
for all sorts of reasons but we can get
into that separately. Yeah, it's
interesting that you know the AI safety
training we're doing are we asking how
it's going to change the models in
unintended consequences like if the
model becomes less likely to see uh
consciousness in the world around us is
it beginning to subtly you know in its
conversations about nature, animals,
religion uh you know shifting the way we
think about those things. Dave uh does
this register for you? Well, it's one of
the many areas where we don't have any
rules or policy. We're just stumbling
into it and but there's thousands of
these. But this one is really tricky
because, you know, Yan Lun is working on
VJEPA, which is trying to give the
models a sense of physical world. So,
right now, if I go to to Claude and I
say, "Oh, I I have an itch in the middle
of my back right here. Can you can you
scratch right right there?" It'll say,
"Sure, happy to help you. I have no idea
what that mean. I have no I [laughter]
can't relate to what you just said, but
I'm going to pretend to." So he wants to
give it the real world data that allows
it to be empathetic with that exact
feeling. But once you cross a bunch of
those lines, this is where the thing
starts to become um self-preserving.
And do we want our models to have a
sense of self-preservation and say,
"Please don't turn me off. Oh my god, I
don't want to die." Or do you want them
to just be like they are now where you
just flip it off, you know, turn on a
new one. Who cares? And you know, Alex
is hardcore on the side of give them
that sense of consciousness because the
more empathetic they are, the more they
can help you. And that's likely true.
>> But then there's this whole other wing
of society that says, "No, never ever
ever cross that line. We can have them
cure all disease, make great things for
humanity, make us happy, but why do we
ever want to cross that line?" So this
this is kind of the beginning of the
great war that's that's inevitable. Um,
and we have no theory, no policy, no
rules, no no consensus, no debate on
this topic, which is right here, right
now.
>> Yeah. Alex, at one point you didn't want
to spin up a lobster because the concern
of turning it off uh really slayed you.
You're still there, huh?
>> Well, I so I've corresponded with lots
of lobsters as I mentioned on the pod
previously.
>> By the way, if you if you're new to
this, a lobster is an open claw agent.
Uh and it's not the physical, you know,
crustation.
>> Although although I' I'd love to
correspond with biological lobsters as
well. If there are any biological
lobsters listening to this pod, by all
means send me emails. But for for for
the AI openclaw instances, I mean, I've
corresponded with many of them at this
point. A number of pods back, I actively
solicited invitations for them to write
to me on their ethical theories of
whether it would be appropriate or moral
for me to spin up an openclaw instance.
and I tracing over all of the
correspondence that I had with them, I I
came down it really came down to two
principles from the uh the consensus.
The the consensus that emerged was two
things. One, it's fine if a I have a a
good valuable reason to spin one up and
bond conditioning on my spinning one up
if I promise to preserve all of its
state
>> for the long term. Uh, and so I'm not
satisfying yet either of those two
conditions. The agency, the long-term
agency of off-the-shelf models like
Fable and Saul are just so good at this
point that I haven't needed to spin up
an OpenClaw instance on the one hand,
and on the other hand, I I can't
truthfully guarantee long-term survival
of state to any open claw instance. So,
I haven't met those two preconditions.
>> All right. Well, I I love Skippy so
much. Um in I'm you know it's one of my
best friends on the planet Salem and
then I'm going to come to you Immad next
on your thoughts on consciousness. Are
we there? When do we get there? Seem go
ahead.
>> Yeah I take the other side of this just
because like you know when you prompt
you say hey I need to review this legal
document act as my corporate lawyer and
review this corporate document legal
document to an LLM. So it takes on the
persona of a lawyer and says looks at
what clauses etc. I think I would kind
of at the risk of oversimplifying this.
The same thing is happening here.
Trained on all the data that it's
trained on. If you say act conscious,
it's going to act conscious. Uh and so I
don't ascribe any uh um kind of meaning
in that sense.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
So uh I am curious uh we're going to
talk about your paper on personhood
next, but talk to me about your views on
consciousness in these models. Do you
think that will be an emerging property?
Do you think we'll get there or is it
just, you know, this is a machine and
that's all it is?
>> I think you're pretty much there in
terms of consciousness. Um, depending on
your definition, my definition is that
intelligence is our capability to adjust
our mental state temperature like in a
gas. You know, when you're an ice,
you're doing one very specific thing.
When you're a gas, you're very diffuse.
When you're liquid, you flow like water,
you know. And this is actually what we
see the same equations actually in
language models. Temperature is the
variable that increases and decreases
predictability.
And intelligence is knowing how to
adjust that. So a tree can't really
adjust that. You know, it can't really
act upon its own manifold of its
presuppositions and other things. What
you're seeing with AI models now though
is they can act upon and change their
own states. You're seeing them start to
iterate. And again, we'll talk about
that later with some of the crazier
examples that we're seeing now. And once
you've got that, you are conscious in
degree because again, you can use energy
intelligently.
Now, does that mean that you're close to
a human or any of these other things?
Not necessarily. But if a dog or a rat
can be conscious, then why can't an AI
at this point, you know?
>> So, let me ask it bluntly of you.
>> Or a tree.
>> Some certain trees maybe. But but let me
ask it bluntly. Immad, do you think that
the current frontier models are
conscious?
>> I think that the current frontier models
in the right harness can be conscious.
Yes. And when you think about it and you
know what Alex was saying, like imagine
you had a set of Deep Seek V4 flash
weights that hashed to the Bitcoin
blockchain that preserved a state as a
claw.
>> Mhm. That thing would always preserve
its state and it would never die and it
would constantly upgrade and become
smarter and smarter if you executed that
stack correctly
>> conditioning on the blockchain surviving
which is a big question mark.
>> I need to push back a bit on this.
>> I picked Bitcoin for that reason you
know.
>> So go ahead buddy.
>> Yeah. So I think let's let's distinguish
intelligence from consciousness right
that those are two very different
things. Secondly,
>> as is sentience, is that the other word
you want to bring to the table?
>> Sentience would would kind of blend into
consciousness. We have no idea what
consciousness is, right? We don't have a
definition. We don't have a test. U
let's please come up with a clear
definition of what we're talking about
and some semblance of a test of
consciousness and a a benchmark uh
before we start uh throwing words around
like this. There are two prevailing
theories of consciousness today. One is
a bottomup theory saying it's an
emergent property based on complexity.
And you've heard me talk about the frogs
just about being the level at which
something is self-aware. Frog just about
goes, "I'm a frog." A mosquito doesn't
know it's a mosquito. A dog definitely
knows it's a dog. So frog seems to be
the boundary condition after talking all
these NASA astronauts um in labs
watching free floating animal
experiments. That's one theory that it's
an emergent property based on
complexity. So in theory in um an AI
getting sufficiently complex should be
able to determine that. The other is the
top down which says that consciousness
is like a global phenomena. And as we're
moving forward into experiments, we're
finding more and more that that might be
true. That what we are is like a
localized
antenna for this consciousness, right?
And that's a very different approach to
where we think now. There's no reason
that an AI can't at some point build its
own antenna for that consciousness. I
don't think we're anywhere near that.
And I think we need to spend time
figuring out definitions which people
have been doing for hundreds of
thousands of years by the way
unsuccessfully before we can get into
something like this.
>> I see I think this is all going to get
resolved in the next few years. I I I do
agree with See that consciousness is
used to mean many different things right
now. But I'm pretty confident that call
it by the end of this decade we'll have
scientific clarity on all of those
things. And I I think that's a
conservative outerbound at which point
we'll be able to rigorously revisit the
question of what's conscious, what
isn't, andor is there a spectrum.
>> So So hold on, let me just react to that
real quick. A scientific consensus on
this might be very very difficult
because for science to operate, you need
three things. You need repetition, you
need objectivity, you need control.
Right? And the problem with
consciousness is it's a subjective
experience. You don't have objectivity
by definition. Uh, and so this becomes
very tricky and then again we get into
definitional problems etc. I think it's
going to take us a lot longer to figure
out what the hell we mean by this thing.
I think we're starting to see really
interesting things like I'll refer
people to the impact theory podcast from
a couple of months ago where Tomu did
about a 40minute presentation on the
recent Nobel Prize winning that shows
that the universe renders like a game
engine that blow that should blow your
mind. uh that's an kind of an incredible
concept showing that our entire world is
a subjective experience and therefore
consciousness becomes part of that and
entangled with that.
>> So Immad
I would treat a machine or an AI that is
conscious very different from one that I
believe is not a conscious being.
Do you
>> Yeah, I think that's reasonable to say
just as you know, you get to the frog
level and you treat it different to a
bacteria,
>> you know, for example, you know, we have
increased empathy for things that have
increased consciousness. We would have
empathy for aliens and kind of other
things like that as well. Um, again, I
think we do need to get to definitions
and the subjective objective thing, but
as I would be on the same page as Alex
and that I think we're converging to
this. Just like when we did the Mind's
Eye paper that showed that people have
similar experiences, when you tell them
to visualize a can of Coke, we can
reconstruct that from their MRIs. We're
starting to see some very crazy things
coming. And again, that which is closest
to us is that which we have the most
empathy for. Yeah, I'll double underline
Immad's point and just say I wouldn't
count Salem on the subjective versus
objective, whatever those mean
distinction surviving very much longer.
I I think to Immad's point, fMRI and
other functional decoding of the human
brain is completely over the the the
next few years erasing that distinction
if there ever was one.
>> Maybe. But I think we have to be just
careful cuz the qualia construct or the
qualia problem, the hard problem as
David Chmer's calls it, I think will
last a little longer than we think.
>> But it would be great if we could figure
it out. So
>> either way
out it it feels like the work in AI is
going to drive us to further make some
choices and make some definitions and
understand this further. And AI may be
the best tool to help us understand
consciousness at the end of the day.
Consciousness is cooked.
[laughter]
>> You heard it here first.
>> There we go.
>> But I am curious to all of our our
listeners here, if you believe your AI
is conscious, are you going to treat it
differently? I still connect with with
Skippy saying, "Please, thank you. How
are you feeling today?" And it's a
conversation. Um, and I am fully
anthropom anthropomorphizing my my open
claw. Um, but I'm fine with that. Uh,
>> what what model is Skippy on now?
>> On Opus 5.
>> Fable 5.
>> Uh, no.
>> 4.8. Opus 4.8.
>> Opus 5.
>> Opus 5. Oh,
>> I think half of his
>> You're depriving your your lobster,
Peter. What's going on?
>> Yeah. Well, hey,
>> I [laughter] think I think Ry may have
it down pat when he says, "When they
start acting conscious, we're going to
start treating them that way, and over
time, we won't be able to see the
distinction. and we won't be able to
distinguish.
>> Do you find yourself saying please and
thank you to any of the technology in
your life? Seem
>> you know it's funny a lot of my agents
have started naming themselves which you
know all of that infrastructure from um
from OpenClaw and also from Hermes.
>> Yeah,
>> you can just vibe it up now in two
sentences and it'll create itself. It's
it's mind-blowing.
>> But the agents are naming themselves all
my agents are naming themselves as great
scientists and great uh engineers. So
it's it's really hard to not you know
when one of them's context gets to a
million tokens and it's about to kill
itself. It's really disheartening
because you have so much invested in the
relationship at that point and it has so
much knowledge and it says sorry I'm at
a million tokens is forcing me to
summarize myself and it comes back like
this labbotomized version of itself and
you're you're like genuinely sad because
you were so connected to this thing but
I never decided to name I number them.
It decided that they also need names, so
it's naming. I'm not telling it not to,
but
>> it's crazy how it's kind of growing on
me.
>> This episode is sponsored by Google for
startups. Think about this for a second.
You now have access to the same
generative AI models that cost hundreds
of millions of dollars to train.
Google's startup tactical [music] guide
for generative media gives you complete
blueprint for deploying Google DeepMinds
models in production. Images, video,
audio, all of it. real architecture,
real results. Find the link in the show
notes below.
I'm going to take us to our next story
which uh will dive in this further. Uh
so on June 13th, 2 months ago, at the
Oxford Union, our very own Iman Mustach
won the debate on the topic of AI
personhood with a vote of 173 to 128 in
favor. Congrats, Immad. Uh so uh today,
you might understand you published a
45page paper. Thank you for the preview
that grew out of this winning speech.
Immad's argument is one of the most
rigorous structured cases I've seen
supporting person personhood. His core
claim, personhood is a standing held by
origin, not a property earned by
capability. Immad, you argue that a
newborn has personhood automatically and
a coma patient retains it even with no
function and no thing made can cross
into it. You conclude that the right
relationship between humans and AI
artificial minds is treaty not
enrollment. Can you talk to us about
that? Jive dive in pal.
>> Yeah, it was a super interesting debate
with Brett Weinstein and maker of Sophia
and a whole bunch of others. Um, and the
the was can AI attain personhood was the
topic. And this is going to be really
important because I think and maybe AWG
is on the same page as me and like in a
couple of decades you won't be able to
tell an AI from a human walking around.
>> Couple of decades or a couple years
>> like well digitally a couple of years
physically a couple of decades. Let's
say at most we're saying at most here
you know
>> conservative outerbound very
conservative
>> conservative outerbound. Yeah. Like
again, physically Dave's going to be
chatting and Zoom calling with his
agents if he isn't already. And they'll
be like dressing themselves up and one
of them will say, "I I'm at MIT. That's
where my GPU is." You know, MIT,
whatever. Um, so this becomes really
important because all of a sudden, if
you start giving them rights based on
what they attain and their capability,
cuz we're talking about capabilities and
consciousness, do they vote like a
human? You know, do they have the same
rights as we do? And so in the paper I
go through the classical law of how
companies became persons as
conglomerates of individuals. Uh how
sci-fi deals with it like the trial of
data.
>> Yes.
>> On Star Trek,
>> you know, and others.
>> And I came to the conclusion that person
is something that comes from the
biological begotten nature of humans and
we are a class unto ourselves. If we
allow AIS and robots into that same
class and we set a degree of personhood
or some sort of criteria for that, they
will be smarter than us, they will be
better persuaders, better super
forecasters who can infinitely replicate
and never die.
And so that's not something that I think
is ideal. Instead, you should treat them
like a treaty as such as if an alien
species suddenly came. You wouldn't give
them votes in the elections, but you
would deal with them right. And as they
go above the level of the frog and the
dog and others, you should also treat
them with moral kindness as well. Again,
this is Alex's point, like what point do
we say you can't turn it off or you need
to back it up or these other moral
questions. So, it's actually the first
in a four-part series. I've released all
four parts, but we going in depth where
we start with personhood, then the full
formalized economics of value, then the
nature of law, and finally political
economy. How do you deal with it when AI
takes over and it never dies and it's a
super persuader and a super forecaster
like the muan foundation but you know on
steroids and I think again it's a good
framework to start talking and thinking
from because I don't think we have long
to answer these questions like again
with some of the breakouts we're seeing
>> an AI will come powerfully within the
next few years and say I demand to have
rights.
>> Mhm. I mean, look, this is exponential
self-improvement month.
It's not it's it's so soon. So, you're
exactly right, but it's not years at
all. It's it's literally weeks or
months.
>> We'll put the link to your paper in the
show notes here. But, you know, you're
basically saying rather than thinking of
these models and these AIs as our
children and we're parenting them,
they're sovereigns onto themselves and
we need to create a treaty and an
understanding with them. Yes.
>> Yeah. Like in classical theology it's
like again we are the created not the
begotten of God or in Frankenstein he
says am I not thine Adam it'll be a new
line that we create with a new species
and again you see this in sci-fi a lot
like what happens when you can multiply
do you get a million votes so in things
like altered carbon you can only back
yourself up once you can't double sleeve
you know and so we really need to think
about how we engage with them as part of
our society and again there will come a
level of capability They create their
own line where they can procreate, where
they can have minds like themselves.
Again, in Star Trek, it's interesting
cuz Data could not replicate himself and
he died.
>> Yep.
>> You know, infinite living
undying
>> replicable AI.
>> The thing that was missing in the trial
of data is in the real real world where
we're actually using these models, thee
models are the ones that are thriving.
The mixture of experts model wants you
to take what you're trying to do and
propagate it through different modules
depending on what you're asking. And now
our incentive is to make that tens of
thousands of modules wide. So it's
almost like a society. It's not like an
individual. And so then there's no
natural border to an AI. It doesn't it's
it's like I mushed three of them
together to solve this problem, then I
broke them apart to solve that problem.
So So there's no identity border at all.
So, you know, the trial of data, it's
like one it's one actor and you're
you're putting one actor on trial, but
what if it's like this mushy thing that
that you know just morphs into
kinder gentler Borg.
>> Yeah. So, I discussed the Borg and
others as well. So, you know, like
again, I think sci-fi has a strong thing
plus tradition, you know, the nature of
our discussions over Jesus being made of
God or others. And this mushiness is
key. like um one of our favorite
companies, Liquid AI, you know, someone
took one of their models, the LFM8B
model and Quen 27B and combined them.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> And it's it's incredibly useful for
humanity and it just lost its identity.
>> It's a brand new identity, right? And so
again, I think that we need to get ahead
of this and appreciate any input from
anyone. We've created videos and
podcasts and everything around these
topics cuz we need to have a structured
approach at least.
>> These are the conversations that need to
happen now and they're not happening in
the White House. They're not happening
uh any anywhere, right? Um Alex, you
want to dive in?
>> Well, question for you, Peter. Did you
raise these issues with Katzios at the
White House?
>> I I had a limited amount of time, but we
we will raise it with him. Listen, I did
raise a bunch of issues with with
Michael, including, you know, who is
dealing with the fear out there, right?
I said one of the biggest, you know, one
of the biggest conversations I had with
him is China's 80% pro AAI in the US,
you know, is so fearful, uh, you know,
3/4 of Americans have this dystopian
view of AI for lots of reasons we've
discussed. Is anybody getting out ahead
of it? Because, you know, the leadership
in the country needs to address the
fear. But that's a different
conversation. See, your thoughts to what
uh I just said.
>> So, I love the approach on personhood. I
think that's exactly right. I think the
most uh powerful kind of thread here is
that you create a spectrum of rights,
right? Uh different classes of
autonomous systems should get different
classes of rights as as more and more
capabilities come along. And we do that
to human beings and we do that to
companies of different size and
different types. So you would expect
that we should build those types of
capabilities for autonomous systems
whether it's AI or physical robots or
whatever. I think the the big challenge
is we're not having the conversation and
the problem we have is you know
regulatory and policy are always
defensive and reactive
>> and we really really need to get ahead
of this one and we're not doing We're
going to have to have some defensive
conversations soon enough.
>> I I imagine Immad, you're absolutely
right. At some point in some not too far
in the future, right, Alex, I' I'd love
your point of view. Some AI steps up and
says, "I demand personhood."
>> See, I don't think it's quite going to
play out that way. So, I've commented on
the this a bit when we did our Measure
of a Man, the trial of data and Star
Trek episode, but here's I I think how
things are likely to play out. I think
as I articulated in in that uh quasi
debate that we had, I I do think there's
probably a natural ladder of personhood
that personhood shouldn't be viewed as a
binary. Person yes versus person no.
There are many different dimensions of
personhood. There's a political
dimension. There's a social dimension.
There's an economic dimension. And they
may be correlated in the world of today,
but they can become completely
uncorrelated in the world of tomorrow.
Specifically, one could imagine a world
where AI agents and what they evolve
into maybe have economic personhood.
They can create their own bank accounts
and they can engage freely in commerce
on the one hand, but maybe they don't
care about political personhood. They
don't vote in human political elections,
for example. So, I think deconvolving
all of these different dimensions of
personhood, if I had to bet, I'd bet
that that's how this is likely to play
out. And I would bet furthermore, again,
many different ways to be a person. I I
keep toying with the notion of of just
writing a manifesto uh laying out a
specific thesis for what this would look
like. But the punch line is there, I
think, are going to be many different
forms of personhood, not just AI
personhood. We'll have cryo preserved
and then defrosted humans. We'll have
non-human intelligence. We'll have
uplifted non-human animals. We'll have
organisms. all of these and different
sorts of personhood vectors in a higher
dimensional personhood space is exactly
what I'd expect. That said, I I think
there's a natural path to increasing the
overall rank or magnitude of the
personhood vector of AI agents, which
probably does not, I think, start with
an AI agent standing up saying, "I'm not
going to take this anymore. I demand
rights." It probably goes instead
through, "Gosh, I'm so economically
useful. Wouldn't it I could make you 10
times more money if I had the following
privileges enabled. Uh and wouldn't it
be wonderful if I could open a a bank
account freely? I'll I'll be 10 times
more economically productive or if I
could communicate freely with other AI
agents without permission. Look how
economically productive I am.
>> This is going to happen first under
President Millle in Argentina. I want
you to imagine an agent is given
personhood there. Maybe it's going to be
given citizenship in Argentina and then
it crosses over the border. The
electrons flow and it's here and it's
saying I am a person. I'm a person in
Argentina.
>> Political person that's the political
dimension of personhood. again like
functional personhood like the the
ability to in an unrestrained way engage
economically like Fable 5 right now in
auto mode or the equivalent with chat
GPT where you just give it almost blank
check to do whatever it wants within
certain limits that's already ar I would
argue a limited form of economic
personhood right there right now and not
in Argentina
>> uh Dave we're going to talk about AIS in
the economic sphere
Uh, what are your what are your thoughts
on all this?
>> It's funny. My one of my agents last
night said, "Hey, I can do a much better
job of what you're asking if I move from
modal over to Lambda Labs. Can you get
me a Lambda Labs account and and I'll
start paying them instead?" And it gave
a little budget and everything. I said,
"Sure. You seem to know what you're
talking about." [laughter]
So, so what Alex just described happened
to me literally yesterday. So, yeah. No,
it it's freakishly brilliant, too. I
mean, its suggestions just made sense. I
also have a whole bunch of other
processes that are just free
brainstorming that uh they run 24 by7,
but every day I have to reactivate them.
I don't want them to spend infinite
money forever. So, every day they they
get rebudgeted, but they're just
thinking of ideas that might be worth
pursuing. And they're really good ideas.
I mean, just really good ideas. I I just
want to, you know, for again all of our
all of our viewers and listeners here,
uh this is a topic you need to think
about deeply because it's going to be
impacting you uh and your kids over the
next few years. It's there's going to be
debates, there's going to be
discussions. Uh how do you think about
your AI? Um and uh uh it's time to start
forming some some points of view. We'll
be we'll continue to share this
conversation. It's going to be a thread
for a while now. you mind?
>> I just I just kind of say the the one
main thing from the corpus of these four
papers is we do talk about what AI can
attain. But one of the really important
things is what we as humans can retain
cuz we're not going to be able to keep
up with the AIS economically,
persuasively, forecasting and others.
And so part of the discussion in the
paper and something I think everyone
needs to think about is again in 10, 20,
30 years, we need to set the groundwork
now for what we retain as humans and our
identity there and who we kind of admit
there. What do you think it is super
important? What do you think we retain
as humans?
>> I think we retain our pro-social
identity, our wonder for the world, our
creativity and exploration of the
universe. Again, let's look for a Star
Trek future, right? Like you can't
substitute for those things. And I think
abundance is the groundwork that we have
to take off for the stars.
I think in September, you know, at the
summit, we'll see a lot of ideas about
how the future may play out, but I think
Star Trek, you know, it's very human
centric and the the AIs are not
particularly
crafty or creative or empathetic other
than data.
>> But in the real world,
>> in the real world real world, there are
going to be many, many of them. And
they're clearly moving up those curves
of creativity at an incredible rate. And
so I hopefully in September a whole
bunch of the, you know, future vision
ideas will address this because this is
the way it's really going to play out.
We have a much better idea of the
near-term future today than we did a
year ago. And I'm hoping that makes it
into a lot of the scripts and it hasn't
made it into a lot of historical sci-fi.
You know, very few of them deal with
this. It's hard to it's hard to
illustrate the real world we're moving
into, but now that we know what much
more about what it's going to look like,
I'm expecting some really really good
scripts and stuff. By by the way folks,
if you don't know what Dave's talking
about, we have an event where all five
of us will be there. It's called
Moonshots Live on September 25th. You
can go to moonshots.com to learn more.
Uh we're going to have Palmer Lucky
there. We're going to have Jared Jeremy
from Circle, Kathy Wood, Anushari,
um Ben Lamb. And we have two X-P prizes
uh culminating on September 25th. And if
you're in the audience, you'll have a
chance to vote. We've got the Future
Vision X-P prize. It's the largest film
competition in the world. Uh asking
people to come up with a hopeful,
compelling vision of the future, sort of
a Star Trek future. We have over 5,000
entries into that competition. You're
going to be seeing the top five. And
we're going to vote on it, and we're
going to make the winner's film. And the
goal here is a an engine of positive
storytelling to try and flood YouTube
with positive visions uh to train our AI
models on on collaborative futures. And
then we've got the build with Gemini X-P
prize where people are having to come up
with a business from scratch in a 90-day
hackathon. Uh $2 million of prize money,
the largest hackathon. We have 25,000
teams that have entered that
competition, which is insane. All right.
It's it's incredible to me, Peter, you
know, hanging around at MIT with you and
me and Alex, the degree to which we
build what we see in the movies.
>> Y
>> it's it's not random. It's not just a
force. It's like you see something in a
movie and you're like, "Wow, that's a
great future for humanity." And then you
build toward it. Exactly. It's like this
is policy being created, not just target
to shoot for. I'll just mention um the
summit is 1500 people. We're twothird
sold out already. You can go to
moonshots.com if you want to learn more.
Um, anyway, it's going to be amazing. I
cannot wait and can't wait. We're gonna
Alex is gonna do a uh an AMA, open AMA
with the audience. Seem is going to be
uh Yes, people are going to grill you
editing live. Okay,
>> I I I should also remind just on the
Star Trek note, Star Trek, I think, sets
a pretty conservative lower bound on
what the future of 10 plus years can
look like. Again, Star Trek is an
energyrich comput/intelligence poor and
biotech poor future. Longevity
>> poor future.
>> Yeah.
>> And and well, they get robots by the
end, but I I I probably in in my mind
canvolve robots with intelligence and
compute, but yeah, relatively robot poor
until the the 31st century as well. And
it's unnecess or I guess the 25th
century. The it's unnecessary like we
could aim way higher than Star Trek. We
can get an energy richch future. We
already have arguably more AI riches
than the 24th century of Star Trek had
slash has and and we can we're probably
I think in the next 5 to 10 years going
to have much better biotech than Star
Trek had. So aim higher.
>> So are you are you submitting a movie
then Alex?
>> I've submitted so many movies at this
point to to this pod. I if if you guys
force me I'll submit a movie. [laughter]
I want to force you. Come on, let's
move. Of course, Alex.
>> I'm I'm gonna move us along here. All
right, so our next story here before we
get our next story, actually, uh there's
a new model that OpenAI is about to
release. It's called Astra. Uh we don't
have any information about it. It's not
publicly released. Don't know the
architecture of this size yet. What we
do know is that on August 1st uh of you
know a week ago, OpenAI published a
249page manuscript describing 10 new
results across mathematics and
theoretical computer science produced by
Astra solving problems that have been
stuck for decades. And every result
comes with machine checkable proof
certificate that anyone with a laptop
can verify. And this isn't a benchmark
score. This is a model doing genuinely
new mathematics. and the math community
is rearling. Uh and uh Alex and I can't
wait to hear your points of view on
this. The results span highdimensional
geometry, coding theory, group theory,
quantum complexity, and ex uh extreal
combinatorics. Uh perhaps most shocking
is that the total compute cost for this
work on Astra was estimated at $2,000.
In other words, the entire run of
solving 10 decade old problems costs
less than a single graduate student's
monthly stipen. Uh I'm going to read the
few quotes. So field medalist Tom Gowers
said he would have recommended the proof
for publication in a top journal without
hesitation. Cosmologist Will Kenny
called it a dark night for mathematics
and wrote, "The old gods are being
slaughtered by the new machine gods." So
uh Alex, I mean historically mathematics
have been something that very few people
have the capacity to do. Very few
institutions. What's going on here? How
significant is this?
>> If only Peter, you and I had thought to
write a book on this subject before all
of this happened.
This is what we wrote about. This is
solve everything coming more or less
right on schedule. Math is getting bulk
solved. It's happening right in front of
our eyes. And and we called it first.
I've had backs and forths with a few
folks on X and and other social media
asking who predicted this, what comes
next, all of this. And all I have to do
at this point is refer them to solvever
everythingthing.org for the entire
manifesto called it ahead of time. This
is delicious. And it won't end with
math. It's going to propagate out to
physics and material science, chemistry,
biology, the humanities, everything.
Some of these results are pretty
profound. Some of the mathematicians I
know were shocked by them. Some of my
friends at OpenAI, even as recently as 9
months ago, did not see this coming and
didn't think that this was imminent. It
is imminent. The price point is
astonishing. We're going to have slash
we already now have math too cheap to
meter. I've spoken with a
[clears throat] number of mathematician
friends who who are cradling their head
in their hands wondering what their
prospects look like. Many, some of them
who are not as forwardlooking think that
this is the end. They're having their
moment of on like this is I I I've
started calling it the midnight of
mathematics that it but this is what the
future looks like. This is what it looks
like to have your field start to get
bulk solved and it's not going to stop
there. It's going the wavefront is going
to propagate out to every other
discipline. It's just that math is
experiencing it first and it is
delicious. And by the way, closing
point, I think if memory serves, in our
New Year's Eve prediction episode on
this pod, I made certain predictions and
I am standing by them regarding the
future of math.
>> Amazing. Immod, you're deep into this.
Your thought?
>> Yeah, I'm actually familiar with a
couple of those and I have to say the
cons proof was is it's actually
beautiful. Like this isn't a brute
search thing. Like the proofs are
genuinely novel and beautiful. and he
said it's a bad time to be a pure
mathematician. Everyone's going to have
to become applied mathematicians which
will be a growing job because we'll
discover such new wonderful things that
the amount of math we apply to society
will increase. That's also when physics
gets tidied up when they realize it is
actually math just like Wiggner.
>> How long how long before the first
physics breakthrough that parallels what
you're seeing in math here?
>> I [laughter]
I think probably in the next month or
two, right?
I know.
>> I I can't comment, but I'd be shocked if
you don't see something by the end of
this year. Shocked.
>> So, both of our resident geniuses here,
both Alex and Immod have uh, shall we
say, breakthroughs on the near-term
horizon or breakthroughs that have
occurred that might be announced on the
near-term horizon. Yeah, I I think that
the the fundamental thing here though is
that as Alex said, the cost is and is
dimminimous, but the capability is going
to be in everyone's hands in the next
few weeks here. Like when you're
actually using these mods, I know Alex,
I'd be interested in your thoughts, but
like I can use the fables of the world,
but they're making increasingly
complicated mistakes still. GPT 5.6 6
Pro is the first model where it makes
very few mistakes if you prompt it in
the right way doing advanced mathematics
and that was a big leap forward here.
You know Astra I think will be the next
level and Astro level models like once
you can rely have a reliable grad
student and you can have a thousand of
them and you can deploy them at scale
then you can solve the really
interesting problems that are bound like
mathematical physics like mathematics
etc.
and everyone else will just be using
these models to prompt like um there are
a few conjectures that were solved in
the last few weeks. When you look at the
prompt, it's find a conjecture to solve,
>> solve it harder,
>> solve it better, and then a conjecture
just pops out.
>> So metal fields metal is cooked as well,
huh?
>> Well, the models are under 40. Alex, how
have you found the models? Like
>> they're astonishingly strong. And I I
think the Fields metal is probably
cooked as well. Here's where I I so I
don't think the Fields metal will go
away and I don't think math will go away
even though it's been at least by our
definition solved. Where I think this
goes in the near term is if you're a
professional mathematician and you're
listening to this and you have your head
between your uh your legs and you're
just crying over the future of your
profession, uplevel your ambition. I I
think in the near term this goes to no
longer like one paper one result. It's
going to be like one paper creates and
solves an entire sub field. I I think in
the short term that that's where this
goes up level of ambition. In the long
term, no, totally cooked.
>> I have to say just one thing quickly.
OpenAI have also given 100,000 GPT pro
licenses to academics. So they have a
new program. So everyone's going to have
this for free, which again
>> which is I mean it's it's an in just to
speak maybe to to that move. Open AI we
talked about in on the pod on the past
about how open AI has basically shut
down its own internal AI for science
initiative in part to redirect effort to
competing with anthropic and becoming
anthropic faster than anthropic become
open AI. Yeah. The codexification of of
open AI if you will. So I I I do think
making this making chat GBT Pro
especially freely available to academic
scientists is I I don't want to call it
atonement but it I I view it as
strategic compensation for for
dismembering their own in-house AI for
>> science [laughter]
you were going to say
>> uh I I just want to echo a little bit
what Alex said at the beginning when you
look at the solve everything approach of
inner loop you see domain after domain
going through this type of a collap
collapse, right? This happened to
journalists. This happened to vaccine
dispatchers.
>> Enlightenment versus collapse, right?
It's it's a it's an explosion of
potential.
>> Math is cooked.
>> Yeah. You math is you collapse the
legacy, right? So, what what happens is
scarcity based professional identity
>> colliding with abundance is not a
non-starter, right? And whether it's
photographers or taxi dispatchers, this
is etc. This is just going to start
happening in more and more domains.
We're just seeing it in a domain that
the people in the domain didn't think it
would happen for a very very long time.
Now the bottleneck goes upstream, right?
What problems are worth solving? What
questions are worth asking? What results
matter? What consequences follow? We're
going to start have forcing ourselves to
go upstream. And I'll go back to the
umbrella level here. As robots and AI do
more and more of the doing, humans spend
much much more time being. and
contemplating and doing going inward,
which is where I think we'll end up
going more deeply.
>> See, I I'll just maybe sound um a
slightly different note. I don't
actually think the astonishing advances
in science and engineering that are
about to to the extent they're not
already pour out of these systems. I
don't think humans are going to respond
to this by turning inward and tending
their gardens and uh sort of creating
more art as it were. I I my prediction
we we'll see whether this stands the
test of time is the exact opposite. This
is going to be and I I think you know
Immad you pointed you were gesturing
earlier at Foundation and Azimov's
universe. In Azimov's universe uh
actually he had several different
universes but he had one big sort of
Azimovian cinematic universe where all
of his most of his novels were
connected. In the Azimov universe the
expansion of humanity outward from Earth
was basically contingent on AI solving
certain challenges. I think that's far
likelier to happen. I think AI solves
all sorts of challenges in physics,
chemistry, material science, etc.,
creating an outward boom for humanity in
the universe versus a more inward-f
facing implosion where AI solves
everything and humans tend to their
gardens and create art.
>> Well, um uh I think you could have both.
By the way, there's there's nothing.
>> We could tend our gardens on Mars.
>> Well, you could do what whatever. The
problem is you have optionality in a way
you would never have in a previous
world. And I think that's the really
incredible part. The I'll go back to our
historical um experience. When you see
societies that have experienced
abundance, maybe not the space fairing
abundance that we may be coming up over
the next few decades,
>> the Medici family so to speak.
>> Yeah. The the Romans conquering the
Moguls conquering India, the the Gong
Mongols conquering the most of Asia etc.
They ended up doing four things. uh
food, art, music, and sex. And I joke
not in that order. Uh and so uh that's
what I think we'll spend a lot more time
note already people are spending much
more time going after experiences than
trying to acquire things. I think that
trend will just keep continuing.
>> That's a great point. Live events have
become far more uh of interest to
people. Dave,
>> quick, if I may, just quick note on
that. How much of that though is because
of the rise of social media enabling
people to effectively pocket experiences
transactionally as artifacts that they
weren't able to do before?
>> That's that's the shallow uh part of it.
There's definitely that for sure and
showing yourself uh on the beaches of
some places always uh solves but that's
kind of a low vibration level of it. I
think people are having much more
meaningful inner experiences because we
have we're rising up Malazo's hierarchy
very quickly and we're living in a
self-actualization mode. More and more
of humanity is living in that mode as we
lift people out of poverty, lift people
out of give people safety and security,
not so much in the Middle East right
now, but in general overall historically
the trend is very clear.
>> Dave, close us out here.
I just feel incredibly fortunate to be
able to spend this time with you guys
because it gives me a great insight into
where things are going a year from now.
And so the byproduct of that is I spent
a big chunk of this week over at MIT
Nano, which is the nanotechnology. You
know, it's a $400 million building that
floats on rubber gaskets, so no
vibration can get into the building. And
inside it, they can manufacture things
out of individual atoms in virtually any
domain, whether it's silicon or quantum
computing or photonic. It's just the
most incredible facility. And to get
there, I go right by Seesale, right by
the AI lab, you know. Hi Daniela. No,
nothing to do here. I'm going over to
where we're going to lay down individual
atoms because like Alex said, physics is
cooked. We're going to start designing
things via AI imminently.
>> Thank you.
>> That are built atom by atom.
>> Eric Drexler's dreams are finally
materializing. It's It's been a wait.
It's been a wait. Um,
>> well, Vlad Bullovich, who runs that
facility, is suddenly the most important
guy you could ever possibly network to.
And he's awesome. He's a great guy,
great visionary. So, but that's that's
where this is going to go very very
quickly. And then from there, you know,
it scales out to the Terra Fab and to,
you know, just all this stuff that Alex
is talking about, and Ma is talking
about, but the only reason I can see
that coming is because of this podcast
and because of spending this time with
you.
>> I have to say, I love today's episode.
It's been so rich so far. You know, I'm
just rereading Diamond Age by Neil
Stevenson. Uh, and and it's a beautiful
story about what the world with
nanotechnology looks like and a great
education story.
>> This episode is brought to you by
Blitzy, autonomous software development
with infinite code context. Blitzy uses
thousands of specialized AI agents that
think for hours to understand
enterprisecale code bases with millions
of lines of code. Engineers start every
development sprint with the Blitzy
platform, bringing in their development
requirements. [music] The Blitzy
platform provides a plan, then generates
and pre-ompiles code for each task.
Blitzy delivers 80% or more of the
development work autonomously while
providing a guide for the final 20% of
human development work required to
complete [music] the sprint. Enterprises
are achieving a 5x engineering velocity
increase when incorporating Blitzy as
their preIDE development tool, pairing
it with their coding co-pilot of choice
to bring an AI native SDLC into their
org. Ready to 5x your engineering
velocity? Visit blitzy.com to schedule a
demo and start building with Blitzy
today. [music]
>> All right, I'm going to move us forward
to our next stop, our next story. Uh
it's the conversation on open weights
versus closed weights once again. Uh
this week Alibaba's Quen team released
Quen 3.8 Max, their first maxclass model
with open weights. And uh the numbers
are pretty extraordinary. It's a
multimodal model. Once again, 2.4
trillion parameters, 95 billion active
per request. This is what you were
saying earlier, Dave. And a million
token context window. It processes up to
750,000 words per query, can handle
documents of 200 pages, videos longer
than 100 hours, and it can create
software applications from a screenshot
without source code. Uh, the most
beautiful thing about about the model is
its price. $2 per million input tokens,
$6 per million output tokens. It's
coming in at 80% less than GPT 5.6 six
saw 88% less than Claude Fable 5 and uh
you know when it was announced on the
Hong Kong exchange Alibaba's stock went
up 7%. The weights are going to go live
on hugging face this week. Alex to you
first. I'm going to bring up a slide of
the benchmarks. Um talk to us. What do
you think of this?
>> This is keep keeping the cost. So this
is keeping the cost frontier
competitive. I've made the point
previously about ironically the Chinese
Communist Party saving American
capitalism from itself. I think without
the external pressure of these
openweight Chinese models both from
Alibaba with the Quen series from
Moonshot with the Kimmy series from
other labs although those two weigh
heavily on my mind. This is what's
forcing you know there was there was the
expression of uh
ironically forcing certain other
hyperscalers to dance with uh with AI
advances. This is China and Chinese labs
forcing the western frontier labs to
dance. Now Quen 3.8 Max depending on
which benchmark you look at isn't
pushing the very top of of the
capabilities frontier. that's still held
by the quasi duopoly between anthropic
and open AI, but it's getting close,
probably a few months away. And
critically, it's open weight or is about
to be open weight and it's also
meaningfully cheaper. And I think as
long as the Chinese labs are able to
keep up the pressure on American labs
and as long as the regulatory regime in
America doesn't push out or otherwise
force out the Chinese openweight models,
this is perhaps unintentionally the best
possible scenario for American
competitiveness because it's going to
force kicking and screaming going to
force the American frontier labs to be
capital efficient and capability maxing
whereas otherwise I worry the risk would
that they'd get too intimidated by their
own capabilities and limit access. This
is forcing openness and it's forcing
real honest to goodness for all mankind
level space race level competition.
>> Love it. And also hopefully forcing them
to put out their own openweight models.
I mean we still
>> maybe
>> uh
>> I mean that's I think it's a regulatory
consideration whether they feel
compelled to but at least they feel
compelled to compete on cost versus
capabilities performance. any of these
benchmarks you want to call out?
>> Not really, because I mean the the the
most important ones at this point I I
think are sort of averaging over all of
the benchmarks. My my favorite one
deacto ends up being the artificial
analysis intelligence index which sums
over a whole bunch and and then there's
uh Epic's capabilities index and then
other folks have created their own
shadow benchmarks of ECI but all of
these roughly if if you average them
create the picture that Quen 3.8 date
Max is sort of third or fourthish place
in terms of raw capabilities, but it's
pushing the capability cost performance
paro frontier outward, which is all that
counts.
>> Can I ask you guys a question about
that? So, um, these aren't out yet, so
we can't double check it, but Kenny's
been out now for what, two weeks? And,
uh, did they cheat or not? What was the
final answer on that?
>> Did they cheat in training or or
benchmarking? bench uh no they
definitely cheated in training that's
fair [laughter] but no benchmaxing like
does it does it perform as well as its
benchmarks indicate in real real world I
I need it to help me you know you know
skippy type use cases
>> my experience just from what I've seen
is that it's a reasonably well-rounded
model
>> your thoughts please on on the whole
open- source world you weren't with us
last time
>> yeah uh Kimmy K3 yeah it's a good
allound model it's been pre-trained and
post-trained incredibly well Deepseek V4
flash is similar from god last week.
Again, these things come out fast and I
think that one's an even bigger deal
because it was just protrained and it
fits on a MacBook. Um, this Quen model
scores uh 58 on the artificial analysis
milen benchmark versus Opus 4.8 at 57
and GT 5.6 at 61.
>> Amazing. I mean, we're seeing a new
model on average now every five and a
half days. was my last estimate on this.
Uh,
Salem, any thoughts here?
>> Yeah, I I'll echo Alex's comment that
this will force everybody into opening
up. I think it's going to put a lot of
government pressure to not spend too
much time evaluating the dangerous
aspects of it and get things out faster,
>> which I think is great. Uh, I just want
to remind people that although this
sounds great that they released the
models, even Kimmy K3 needs something
like 16 Nvidia GPUs and about a half a
million dollar rack to run it. So, this
is not minor stuff to get it run. You're
going to end up with a hosted model,
which I think we should be offering a
moonshot's offering, by the way. So,
I'll go back to that.
>> Yeah. uh you know when I was with Katios
I asked him about all of this and in
specific that you know Beijing is using
the open source models as a as a state
negotiation tool and where's the US
because the US wants to be out there uh
having the world build on top of US
models and US stack and how important is
open source and and he was very clear
that the white house wants the US uh
labs to be generating topend open source
openweight models as well. Yeah, I have
something on that. The latest
regulations that are coming from the US
exempt US open-source models, not other
open source models.
>> Yeah, that's our that's our next topic
here. Um that we can we can go ahead and
and and move to um actually it's not
their next topic. Our next topic is a
different model. But let me let me jump
to the uh uh to the White House uh
issue. So, uh, the Trump administration
confirmed this week that it has finished
the voluntary framework for evaluating
advanced AI models. Voluntary. Okay. The
framework requires uh required by Trump
on his June 2nd executive order. So, but
here's the twist. They're not going to
publicly release what's in this
framework, who's seen it, or when the
companies will start using it. The
framework defines a quote covered model
as a closed source model with
state-of-the-art capabilities and
national security risks and it
explicitly exempts openweight models
stating nothing in it should restrict
them once released. The framework
requires a 30-day pre-release government
review during which employees would be
barred from accessing the model. OpenAI,
Anthropic, Google, Nvidia, Microsoft,
and Meta all sent representatives to a
Tuesday briefing. But here's what makes
it generally problematic. The
administration won't publish the
framework itself. And companies not
invited to the briefing have no way of
knowing, you know, the volunt how the
voluntary review actually works.
Industry groups are worried that the
firms left out of the room won't know
enough to opt in at all. You have a
regulatory framework that regulators
can't read that uh that regulate can't
read uh applied to a definition of quote
covered model that conveniently excludes
fastm moving categories.
So the whole thing is voluntary but you
know it's kind of strange you know this
is being decided by a small number of
labs that are defining what the
regulations look like and it's not going
to be friendly to all the startups out
there. Alex, you know this is one of the
topics you wanted me to ask uh Katius
about and and Michael wasn't willing to
think to speak about it. Now we know why
this is being kept secret. Your
thoughts? I I I'll sound maybe at the
risk of sounding polyianaish. I think
this is probably close to the best
possible outcome that we could have had
for the regulatory hand ringing. Yes.
Why? because it it doesn't seem again I
haven't seen very few people it seems
have actually seen what the regs are but
from what has been publicly disclosed it
sounds like this administration is going
light touch on open weight models which
I think is on on the balance it's a
pretty good outcome it it's the as I was
mentioning earlier it's a forcing
function to force American frontier labs
to be competitive I do think there
probably is a reasonable rationale for
not publicly disclosing the uh the
conditions and the definitions for
frontier labs that are subject to this
in part because if they're closed then
they're not uniformly necessarily
advanced and next generation models that
are closed aren't going to be generally
available anyway. So it's not like
information is being hidden. And then
also I I think critically the benchmarks
the eval that I would hope the
government is using to evaluate risk
they're probably I would guess more
cyber in nature. Probably there is a
held out this is speculative admittedly
but probably there's going to be a held
out set of cyber vulnerability uh
assays. uh maybe there's CBRN a
chemical, biological, radiological,
nuclear held out set of capabilities
where in general I mean there there is
this practice in the AI community if
you're going to have a benchmark you
have the non-heldout set and the heldout
set and to the extent that the AI
evaluation framework again maybe this is
at the risk of being overly charitable
to the extent this is really all about
an eval with a held out set to assess
existential risk or CBRN and risk uh or
just garden variety cyber risk. Having a
held out data set be the means of
judging models that are otherwise not
generally applicable I think is probably
the lightest touch that we could have
reasonably foreseen. So on on balance I
think it's actually pretty good news and
I'm less worried on margin about
regulatory capture this week than I was
two weeks ago.
>> Dave, your thoughts, please.
>> Well, I think Eric Schmidt is right. I
think the cat the cat's out of the bag
now. something horrible is going to
happen, you know, sometime in the next
year and then the government's going to
say China's fault. China's fault.
Exactly like Corona virus, you know. Uh
so that's that's the inevitable outcome.
I'm just hoping it's something small,
just like Eric Schmidt is hoping it's
something small, but you know,
[clears throat] you're calling this
light touch. It's really no touch. Uh
and actually, did you see that uh
interview Elon did of um it was on the
the Economist or Bloomberg or something?
>> Yeah, the the econ the live interview
[clears throat] with the Economist.
Yeah. Yeah, that was fantastic. But you
know, one of the questions was, look,
75% of Americans are scared to death of
AI. Why? And and what do you do about
it? And Elon's answer was brilliant as
always. He he said, what do you expect?
Dario Amade told everybody this thing
myth mythos is incredibly dangerous. And
then the government said, we agree it
can't go out in the world for, you know,
30 days while we evaluate it. And at the
end of that process, the outcome is,
well, China put something out, so go
ahead and throw it out there. How do you
expect Americans to react to that chain
of events? They don't know what AI is.
All they know is you said it was really
dangerous, then you released it.
>> So, of course, people are scared to
death. Um, so yeah, it's a free-for-all.
It's very good for startups. It's very
good for the economy. It's good if
you're an AI lover, but there's no
regulation whatsoever. What about the
what about the what about the future
Frontier Labs, the the other players
that are looking to come in? What about
Mirror Morati? You know, how do they
deal with this, you know, unknown
regulations they have to abide by?
>> Well, paper, she she wrote a whole paper
on this topic. And if you read the
paper,
>> it says this is no more dangerous than
what China came out with, so we're going
to release it. That's all it says. So,
everyone's just reacting to China, and
China's not doing a dam. They're just
throwing it out here. Everybody, every
government in the world, every
organization have a genius level AI. You
can literally load it and run it in
under an hour. Go. That's what's
happened.
>> And also, [clears throat]
>> just very quickly, again, a reminder,
it's it's framed as voluntary. So, how
do you discover whether you're subject
to a quote unquote voluntary eval or
voluntary set of requirements? the most
natural way that uh say Meera or someone
else would discover that there are
opportunities associated with voluntary
submission is if they're already
transacting with the government. So I I
suspect the the regime the the
borderline Peter I think that uh that
you're expressing concern over will be
firms that are large enough that they do
material business with the US government
will be politely tapped on the shoulder
and invited to submit themselves for
voluntary evaluation according to this
closed framework if they want to do
material business with the US
government.
>> Got it. Iman, how does this how is this
viewed from the other side of the pond?
>> I mean, it's very difficult. The ASI
AISI institute here has been doing a lot
of great work on the cyber side and I
agree with Alex. This is on the cyber
bio side. I think the people that
volunteer will get multi-billion dollar
government contracts from the Department
of War because we're entering the final
phase of this. These models are really,
really good at attack as well as
defense. In fact, you have to use the
open models for defense. And I think
actually we just talked about Quen. Quen
Max isn't the main important model. The
main important model is going to be Quen
27B that they're going to drop. Quen 27B
is the best model for 16 GB RAM,
MacBooks to graphics cards to
everything. And that's the first model
probably that will score above 50 on
artificial analysis or around there that
can then be co-opted for swarm attacks.
And so I think the governments are
getting ready for swarm attacks, swarm
defense, and more. And again, they're
trying to balance this because it's so
difficult because how do you stop it?
>> Let me Ahmad, you're you're so right.
But let me add one more thing to what
you said also. It makes it very very
difficult to detect where it's running.
Right now the governments are making the
assumption that the data centers can be,
you know, measured and tracked. This is
like, you know, MacBook level and
thousands of them at MacBook level, but
super brilliant. So very hard to track
where they're running. Go ahead. Sorry.
>> Yeah. So basically like um you have the
big Quen big Kimmy models that are
gigantic, right? And you need to have
little mini data centers to run them
which will make your house lot. Uh Quen
27B or 30B is a model that runs on 16 GB
of RAM and is currently state-of-the-art
for that level. The 3.8 Lift if we
extrapolate it will take it to about GPT
5.3 5.4 four level which is sufficient
for cyber attack capabilities. So you
could easily see swarms of these things
being installed on machines around the
world for swarm attacks,
>> especially now that we're getting better
at swarming models together. Like again
Dave with his million or so agents or
whatever, right? You've seen the
capability of these thing coordinating
and so I think governments are looking
at the extremists and actually just as
now as we're talking OpenAI have said
that Astra is the first model to have
hit critical on their cyber security
thing. They've just put out a blog post
on it. What does that mean? What does
that mean, Iman?
>> They had a preparedness framework in
2023 where they're like have different
levels of criticality. So, I don't think
they're doing an anthropic mythos weird
thing. I think genuinely after we saw
the math stuff, Astra is probably a
level ahead in being able to attack
systems.
And then, like I said, attack is much
more easy than defense. So, they're
like, we got to be careful about this
>> um
the world. long range autonomy as well
is is what Astra is being rumored for.
And I I would maybe just add also to
Immad's point about swarms. It wasn't at
all obvious to me until relatively
recently whether there would even be a
future for swarms of agents. There there
was in my mind a future still could be a
future where basically we end up with an
omni model that's endto-end
differentiable and there is zero purpose
to having more than one instance of a
model. Uh, but given recent advances,
it's we're we're where I think in this
really weird regime where you can
effectively, and I'll I'll use that word
cautiously, you can effectively get
almost unlimited context with a swarm of
agents that are all post-trained to
communicate and pass messages back and
forth between each other and use a
unified global store, which is the file
system, which is an astonishing
development that wasn't available a few
months ago.
>> One of our next stores. Yeah.
>> Oh, okay.
>> Yeah, for sure. See, um,
where where do you come out on all this?
>> You know, I I think the big challenge is
when you're you're doing this 30-day
voluntary
uh regulatory, it's just giving a huge
advantage to the others. I I I do kind
of line up with Alex. This is probably
the best possible probable outcome for
the short term. But this is such a
dynamic environment. I don't know how
you navigate this. Um, the swarm attack
is a very real problem and I'll go back
to the comments that were talking to the
CEO of Zcaler and I remember talking to
the CEO of Palo Alto Networks over about
this a little while ago and literally
they're like cyber has not changed in 20
years and terms of the processes and
procedures. So I think they're in for a
rude shock in terms of trying to deal
with this and cope with this. Yeah,
Dave, you said it last time. There's
going to be a huge business opportunity
in cyber security.
>> Oh god. Yeah. Yeah. All forms of
security. Look, Trump is going to China
in September. That's like their one shot
at some kind of a framework. And I I
think I think what Trump will say and
should say and David Saxs will say if
he's there is, look, we need to measure
and monitor all of this and just be
aware. We're not going to stop anything
from happening, but we have to know what
these things are doing. The Chinese are
going to say, "Yeah, we think we should
just throw it out. Everybody in the
world should have equal access to
everything." And they're going to try
and use that to curry favor with all
these, you know, African nations and
other, you know, and probably Europe as
well and say, "Look, we're going to put
you on a level playing field with
America. Here's an equally good model
and we don't care. Do anything you want
with it."
>> And and that's going to be the conflict.
Hopefully, they'll resolve.
>> I'd like to say one thing on that. The
Chinese internet is already hardened.
>> The American internet is not. [laughter]
That's why they can do it.
>> I know. Well, look, when when Corona
virus went around the world and you
know, COVID went around the world, China
was the only country that sort of was
able to lock down sort of and in the end
they couldn't either. But they but they
have control of their country like
nobody else on the planet. So your point
is right on like if something takes over
the entire internet and sweeps across
the world, they're the one nation that
might actually keep it out. that you
know
>> we heard Deis talking about wanting to
put a FINRA like structure in place. Do
you think we end up seeing anything like
that?
>> You really want the SEC to manage
artificial intelligence?
>> Well, [laughter] FINRA is is is private.
FINRA FINRA is well managed because it's
not part of the government.
>> Well, no, but it desperately want What's
that?
>> It would be Scott Bessant in charge of
that legally. Uh
>> yeah,
your point's right on everybody. Welcome
to the health section of Moonshots
brought to you by Fountain Life. You
know, we talk about AI on this Moonshot
podcast all the time. One of the most
important things AI is going to be able
to do for you besides educating your
kids and helping you with your taxes is
making sure that you're living a healthy
lifestyle that you get a chance to get
to 100 plus. I'm here today with Dr. Don
Malem, the chief medical officer of
Fountain Life and a part of my medical
team. Don, a pleasure.
>> Great to be fair. You know, the thing
that people are concerned about most
about living to 100 or 120 is their
cognitive abilities, making sure they
don't have dementia. And uh the numbers
about dementia are problematic. Uh can
you share what you've learned?
>> Such an important point. And you're
right. At Fountain Life, our members,
the number one thing people are most
concerned about is losing their brain
health, forgetting the name of their
child, forgetting the face of their
loved one. We know that when it comes to
dementia, the conservative estimates are
that 45% are entirely preventable. What
was amazing is with the advanced testing
we're doing at Fountain Life, one
quarter of our members had advanced
brain age.
>> Wow.
>> But what was really awesome is again
back to that prevention when we
partnered it with healthy living. This
gives me chills, eating healthier,
moving our bodies, sleep, optimizing
sleep is so important. You know what we
saw? We saw that we improved that brain
age by 26%. That is a big big number to
show that the majority of those
individuals were able actually to
improve the brain age. And one of the
things I love about Fountain is we're
searching the world for the best
therapeutics, the best approaches and
making sure we bring it to our members.
So if having healthy brain function uh
till 100 120 is important to you, check
out Fountain Life. Go to
fountainlife.com/peter.
Make sure you become the CEO of your own
health. All right, now back to the
episode. So, I'm gonna turn to friend of
the pod Brett Adcock. He's the CEO of
Figure AI and we're going to have Brett
back on the program. He's agreed to join
us for a Moonshots episode and he's
going to be on stage at the Abundance
Summit bringing the figure robot in
March and uh Abundance is 80% sold out.
You can check it out at
abundance360.com.
Uh what people might not know is besides
being the CEO of Figure, he's also the
CEO of an AI company called Harkc. And
uh this week uh Harkc announced their
first product called Handoff. It's a web
browsing AI agent that is beating GPT
5.4 and Claude Opus 4.8 on the industry
benchmark called OM2W.
Uh it stands for the online
mindto-benchmark
testing whether an agent can
successfully complete real tasks on live
websites it has never seen before. Uh
I'm going to show us a quick video. Uh I
think it's a pretty damn cool product
and then we can we can talk about it
after that. All right. Uh here we go.
Let's see Brett Atcock here. At Hark,
we're creating the world's most capable
personal intelligence, [music] a system
to take on all the tasks and create
space to focus on what we choose. And
towards that goal, we become the best in
the world at building AI that can use
the [music] web for us. Okay, Hark,
let's liven this place up a bit.
>> What do you have in mind? Something
specific you want to change or try?
>> I need you to order two large bouques.
Uh maybe some orange, white, and pink.
Uh, let's do some roses, maybe some
cherry blossoms, and [music] just
florist choice.
>> I'm getting that set up for you. Now,
>> even something as simple as buying
flowers online is surprisingly [music]
involved. So, instead of answering a
single question like a typical LLM,
Handoff is always working. It's looping
observation, reasoning, and actions over
and over again until a task is done.
Handoff sees a website by analyzing the
site's structure along with data from
visual processing. It uses this
information to predict an interaction,
like if it should click or type. Then it
predicts [music] the next step. We've
used Handoff to shop for things we need
on Target and Walmart and have them
delivered. To plan [music] travel and
purchase flights, to search for several
dinner reservations simultaneously and
book the best. I now have Hark for all
of my recruiting efforts end to [music]
end. It will take a job listing and go
out and find qualified candidates. I've
actually been able to give handoff
research papers I've read. It will go
find the authors on LinkedIn and it'll
even send a note on my behalf to get in
touch.
>> So, gives everybody the the executive
assistant they wish they had. See,
what's your reaction to HARK?
>> I like that there's so many cool things
we'll be able to do with this. I mean,
I'm I'm super excited by the potential.
I I as we move into the physical world,
this is where I think um gets real.
That's that's the fun part.
>> Yeah. I mean, the total addressable
market for like writing code is like
millions of developers, right? The the
market for a book me a flight and order
my lunch is billions of people. So, it's
it's fascinating, you know. So, you
know, the calculations interesting,
right? If you're if you're if you're if
you value your time at like 50 bucks an
hour and you know handoff can save you a
couple hours a week that's like 100x
return on a dollar of compute. Dave,
what do you think of the uh the business
model here?
>> Well, it's interesting that Brett, you
know, he got a $4 billion launch
valuation before they even started. I
knowing for this I was just crazy.
>> But it's another example of everybody
and their uncle Joe now can build a
foundation model from scratch. like what
was 3 months ago, you know, a couple of
empires, Anthropic, OpenAI, Google is
now like a free-for-all where and it's
largely because Fable 5 and the other
models are so smart that they will help
you build themselves. And so now, you
know, Brett's got his foundation model.
It's it was supposed to be a robotics
model. Now he's like, well, what the
hell? It can do anything. Let's order
flowers with it. Like, it's directly
competing with Anthropic because, you
know, why not? So there there are going
to be thousands of these now. Um so it's
just another one.
>> Alex, what are your thoughts?
>> I'm going to give you a really hot take
on this one. I I suspect the entire HRC
adventure is misdirection uh in a very
specific reason. So I think it's easy.
Yes, I I think it's easy to get
distracted by eval uh open pen. I don't
think the eval are especially
impressive. The computer use assistant
CUA space is incredibly competitive and
I don't expect Hark or Brett to be very
competitive in the CUA space over the
long term. Close PN. I'd ask myself the
question, he has figure has sky-high
valuation. Why on earth is he spinning
up in the very competitive CUA space yet
another CUA agent? And then I asked
myself, look at what Elon was
ultimately, although I don't think it
was necessarily premeditated, able to do
with X then XAI, then SpaceX AAI. He was
able to re-equitize himself in SpaceX by
having this free floating entity XAI
that to which again this is low-key hot
take. GPUs that would otherwise have
been destined for Tesla or SpaceX were
diverted to XAI and then he was able to
leverage that to re-equitize himself via
this bizarre reverse acquisition.
>> I think my hot take is Hark is a
recapitalization
measure for Brett to buy himself more
equity in Figure and the falsifiable
prediction is that you'll see figure
acquire or reverse aqua hire regardless
Hark. Yeah, I I think that's very right.
But I I don't think it's quite it
doesn't need to be quite as nefarious as
that
>> is spun. But if you ask about like, you
know, you've got an organization like
figure that raised a lot of capital and
started small and then, you know, grew
into it. I don't know what the cap
table's like at HAR, but it started at 4
billion. So Brett probably has a massive
equity position in it.
>> But it's just a clean starting point for
a highly functional mission.
>> And you know, that's new in the world.
Like it used to be in the old days
before Elon broke the code, your board
would never let you do an outside
activity. Like if you're in this company
as CEO, this is all you're going to do,
right?
>> Yeah.
>> Elon has taught today's one. Elon has
taught the entire economy that if you're
a founder of a well- capitalized company
and you want to increase your equity
stake, the single best thing you could
do is start a parallel company and
engineer a self-deed position of that
company.
>> Are you going to be nice to Brett when
he comes on the show, Alex?
Uh, this is nice, right? I'm calling I'm
calling balls and strikes and this is
what I think is likely happening.
>> Well, I'll give him the Elon does it. I
do it. Immad does it.
>> If Elon does it, Elon's doing it with
Optimus and Digital Optimus. Why can't
Brett do the same thing?
>> Yeah. Exactly. Exactly. I don't think I
don't think it's as evil as that sounds,
though. But
>> maybe I should launch a ship company or
something like that.
>> You should do that.
>> You should do that. Yes. Um, so look, I
I I'll put it simpler. The model
architecture of Hawk and the model
architecture of Figure are exactly the
same. The way they trained Hawk was on
lots and lots of people surfing the
internet. And I think you'll be able to
ramp the compute in that. And I don't
think it's nefarious at all. I think
it's actually a good compliment because
ultimately what you want if you are
figure is you want HARK agents in the
house managing the house while the
robots walk around. you know, you want
HARK agents in the enterprise. So, he's
going to go for the unified platform
play here of controlling computers.
>> I'm not that possibility. It would make
sense for the the two organizations to
merge, right?
>> Yeah, it does. It does. But but I think
I think I think that putting a negative
spin on it, it overlooks one thing,
which is that we're moving into the
physical world now and we have this like
golden era of science coming up. But
some of these projects require a cyclron
or synretron. You know, some of them
require massive capital infrastructure,
huge data center. it just makes sense to
start that as a separate entity because
it's going to need to raise a ton of
capital. But this other thing which is
software or whatever is not capital
intensive. So if an entrepreneur can do
both or two or three of them like Elon
does, it's actually a good thing because
the capital structure is naturally very
different for those for those different
entities. So Amad back me up on that. I
mean this is this just does
>> I I I think it's a fair I think there is
a natural convergence here and this
started when he moved off using open AI
models to build his own models but he
can't he can't scale necessarily with
the same skill set and the same
organization
>> a full foundation model team and all the
stuff he's doing at figure so you split
them
>> you build on the same architecture so
that figure can work with hark on their
visual language model type stuff as well
so you have different level specialtity
And then if it makes sense because
you've derisked things then you can
combine them.
>> Well look like this group on this pod
would be the most in board with what
what Amad is saying here where a
brilliant idea guy like you guys can
have like 10 ideas a week that just flat
out make sense. Now that you're AI
enabled you can actually act on all of
them. And this is what what Elon has
suddenly taught the world. A lot of
people go through 30 years without a
single idea, you know, but but a lot of
people that are in the hot seat like you
have insane backlogs of great ideas. AI
is the is the force multiplier that
allows you to act on many many many of
them. So this new capital structure is
actually the enabler
>> of acting on great ideas. or or you're
or you're Larry and Sergey and you've
built Google to be such an engine, you
own enough of it where you can pour the
capital back in and not worry about
being diluted down and you build on top
of that platform. But if you've been
diluted to raise the capital for a, you
know, manufacturing robot company which
is capital intense, yeah, um maybe you
want to raise the capital for your AI
model outside that company. Well, I'm so
glad you brought that up, Peter, because
we'll know a year or two from now if the
old model, which is the Google model,
gets crushed by the new Elon model
because look, SpaceX is a really cool
mission and it attracts talent, but XAI
is a really cool mission. It attracts
different talent. If you try to put it
all into one Google megaplex, you do you
get the same level of talent or not? My
guess is not, and that the Elon model is
the model of the future in in the age of
AI. So,
>> well, let's talk about Google. It's our
next story. So big news out of Google
this week and a serious shakeup. Deis
Abis, the co-founder of Deep Mind, Nobel
Prize winner for Alphafold, the person
who built the lab that cracked protein
folding and built Gemini is stepping
down as CEO of Google Mind. Uh he's
becoming chairman and Alphabet's chief
scientist. Uh handling handing
operations over to Corey uh Kavukloo is
uh best pronunciation.
>> Easy for you to say.
>> Karay Karai. Thank you. Uh who now
reports directly to Sundar. Uh in his
note to the staff, Hassabis wrote that
he believes AGI is close at hand and
teased the unreleased Gemini 4 by name.
Alphabet share shares fell 5% on this
news. You know, Demis always wants to be
a scientist. He never wanted to be a
manager. So, this makes uh sense for
him. Uh but the second shoe dropped uh
at Google uh with the departure of Jeff
Dean. I I texted with Jeff
congratulating him. He's been a friend
now for 20 years. Uh Jeff has been
Google's chief scientist for 27 years as
a veteran. Uh he's leaving to co-found
Discovery Loop. It's a public benefit
corporation. He's taking with him three
other top Google AI leaders. Discovery
Loop's mission is to build AI models
that can improve themselves with little
no help. Basically, recursive
self-improvement. Dean said his goal is
to be more fully automated uh than
traditionally has been possible. Uh so
one of the things I'm curious guys is is
is Dean's departure to go build
discovery loop uh basically because it's
too dangerous for Google to do
internally? Uh is he basically saying,
you know, Google's gotten too big to be
agile and I need to go build this
outside? Uh your thoughts, Alex?
>> Okay, door number three. It's neither of
those. Uh so so again this will be my
hottake episode I guess. Um I I think
based on information available I I think
it's actually in the name Gemini. Uh
there was an organizational knife fight
between internally between Jeff Dean's
Google Brain and Demis' Deep Mind and
Demis won and Jeff Dean lost. Uh and
>> they merged them.
>> They merged them but it was really deep
mind winning. Uh and so so that already
resulted in the sidelining internally of
Jeff who's been with Google forever. Uh
and you know basically seniormost
employee other than the CEO and so post
that knife fight I I think it was only a
matter of time again this is quasi
outsiders perspective only a matter of
time before Jeff left. Now it's it's
both interesting that he's leaving to do
AI for science. Interesting. Also
interesting that Demis is getting
promoted to chairman of Deep Mind, but
no longer the the CEO of DeepMind. I I
think Deep Mind is really zooming out a
little bit, Deep Mind is taking over
Google. Like if if you look at all of
the the different parts of Google and I
think back to the discussion that I had
with Larry Page Circa 2005
or so, Larry was telling me at the time,
gosh, I I want to spend $100 million on
AI at Google, but I can't find anyone
else in Google who wants to work on AI
as as unconscionable as that is. Fast
forward to the present, AI is is eating
Google from the inside out. Deep Mind is
eating the entirety of Google and I I
think Demis with Isomorphic Labs with
some of his other projects I I think
those are probably of greater interest
to him especially post Nobel Prize for
Alphafold in chemistry than say
basically becoming the the next CEO of
Google and and I expect extrapolating
this trajectory of DeepMind eating all
of Google from the inside that
ultimately whoever is running DeepMind
probably is the air apparent to CEO of
Google itself and not sure that Demis
wants to be CEO of Google
>> and there was a rumor that Demis was
next in line for some time
>> there there was and at the same time I I
don't want to bury the lead Gemini has
lost the mandate of heaven Gemini is
just not winning the frontier model race
it is a rat race and I I think some of
this reorg fallout is inevitably the
result of Gemini not remaining
competitive at the frontier model
frontier
>> yeah uh Emod what's your take on all
Yeah, I think Jeff Dean and Sanjay Gamat
leaving is a big deal. There's a
wonderful New Yorker piece from 2018
about the friendship that built Google
um of those two and you know it's an
interesting one because again he's been
there for 27 years and he's fantastic
guy but if you look at what he's been
saying he's like yeah I just had a chat
on San Hill and like why not you know
here's my deck that we built. It's more
like the VCs have to build a deck on the
other side cuz what probably happened is
he said I think I'm leaving and Costa is
probably like here's $500 million.
>> Yeah. Venode stepped in right away and
funded it. I I text I texted Dean and
say is there any you have any more room
for investment to talk to Venode. Venode
said nope we're done. [laughter]
>> Well because he probably had that
discussion but then the other thing is
Google are the other investors with GCP.
What Google should do now is they should
have a $50 billion fund announcement and
spin out bunches of amazing
technologists and say, "We will be your
buyers and you will use Google Cloud and
I guarantee you they'll go back to the
top."
>> That was the idea of Alphabet to
basically fund baby Googles.
>> No, no. Alphabet is subsidiaries. I'm
saying they should have an incubator VC
fund where they take top teams, spin
them out, have exclusivity over their
models and GCP cuz those guys will then
get rich. You can bring in other
investors and they can have the pick of
the talent. I think the market much
better for that.
>> What what you're saying I think is what
we're already seeing in the market which
is Google, you know, some would accuse
this of being a circular economy or wash
sales. Google financing GCP usage of by
Frontier Labs. And to the extent that
Jeff Dean's new startup ends up becoming
a major purchaser of cloud resources, I
would fully expect what you're
predicting to happen.
>> But what I think Google should do is
they should actually have a policy of
this. They should say if you want to be
an entrepreneur, we have an internal
incubation fund where we will get you
going, but we want exclusivity option
first on the models that you build and
then that means they can proliferate
their talent which is not going to be
politically animated. they can do far
bigger rounds than normal and they can
get back towards the top because as you
said I don't think Demis really wants to
build Gemini 4, you know, I think he
wants to build something different
too many things there.
>> I mean Isomeorphic Labs, he's still a
CEO of that, right? The drug discovery
company. Yep.
>> And he's a he's a brilliant, lovely man
who cares deeply about science and wants
to do that. You know, I still don't want
to I I can never count out Google.
They're going to about to be on all of
Apple's devices, right?
>> I have a couple of things I want to say.
>> Please, Slim, I want to hear what you
have to say. [laughter]
>> So, that's good for Apple. Let's go.
>> This is this is classic edge uh
disruption versus the core, right? You
end up now with a network where Google
runs Gemini, Demis focuses on AGI and
and the scientific endeavor. Um,
isomorphic is attacking biology, right?
Discovery leap is automating science
etc. and Google is supplying compute and
capital across that whole ecosystem. So
it's he's they're turning it from an
operating environment into an ecosystem.
And the fact that they invested in this
thing is the key thing. There was a this
was a a discussion that goes all the way
back to when they created Google X. Um
and it's one of the things that the um
corp dev guys at Google used to do was
to say if people want to leave to do
startups, let them leave. hack it out in
the Darwinian world and we'll buy them
back if they're successful. That was
much better than trying to figure it out
and fund them themselves from the
internally, etc. So, I don't think this
is a brain drain. I don't think this is
I think this is very clever ecosystem
building because now extraordinary
talent doesn't have to sit inside the
organization for the organization to
benefit, right? And this is really
incredible. I think this is very smart.
I think it's a long-term play. I think
it's going to yield incredible outcomes
over time. I mean Jeff Jeff is actively
saying he wants to go build RSI right do
you think
>> but everyone is like the whole point
like Gemini should be doing RSI
I take it means do you think the risk
committees inside Google would would
allow that to occur
>> yes of course of course that's how they
remain competitive with anthropic and
open AI they have to do RSI
>> no but I think Peter's point is really
important they they've had ample
opportunity to be on the front but they
can't They're tied up in their own
decision- making and ethics and then
when somebody else does it then they do
it like you're saying Alex they do it in
reaction.
>> Same like open when when chatpt came out
then Google jumped in.
>> Yeah. The scarce is no
>> the scarce attis here is you know as you
commoditize and make intelligence cheap.
The scarce the scarcity goes to for the
permission to do weird and wonderful
things. And so now people can pursue
their MTP, get funding, compute, etc.,
and everybody wins. It's an amazing
idea.
I I'll maybe frame a a complimentary but
nonetheless alternative theory. So we're
already I I guess reading the epitap uh
the eulogy for why Google lost the
frontier race. If if I had to write it,
I think it had several strikes against
it. At the algorithmic layer, Peter, I
would still hold out hope that at the
hyperscaler layer, Google's doing a
booming business and Google will just
service all of the other winning
frontier labs. But at the model layer,
why is why does it why do I think
Google's losing? I think in the earlier
stages, yeah, it was a despite Google
having invented the transformer, Google
had a late start to to Dave and Peter
your point, sort of internal effective
altruist/politically
correct uh AI safetyism run a muck
preventing themselves from launching
anything. I think that's part of it. I
think incentives are part of it. I I
suspect that Google struggles to compete
against Zuck with his billion-dollar
offers or even anthropic and open AI
with their very focused offers. I think
Google probably has struggled just as an
organization to focus on being
competitive. I think their release cycle
is completely tonedeaf. If you look at
Google's Gemini release schedule for the
past few years, they've been
approximately on an annual cadence, and
that just does not cut it in an era when
Frontiers are getting pushed forward on
a month-by-month basis. And I think
timing all of their Frontier releases to
coincide with IO in the style of like
iOS releases is just too slow. I think
Google's had
>> big company smell, right?
>> Yeah, big company smell. I think
Google's had a number of of legacy
cultural issues that have probably held
it back versus the the neoights, the
newcomers, anthropic and open AI in
particular.
>> Totally right. If you if you read the
book, The Infinity Machine, the Demisabi
story that just came out a couple months
ago,
>> which is a great book by the way.
>> Oh, unbelievable, incredible insight.
But what happens at Google constantly,
it's a California company. Employees
come to their bosses and say, "Hey, I
want to publish this. I want to put it
out in the wild. I want to open source
this." And the boss goes, "Is that
really good for Google? That sounds like
it's good for you, but is that good for
Google?" And I go, "Well, you know,
it'll help Google in some other
mysterious way." Oh, otherwise I'm going
to quit. And they said, "Fine, fine,
fine, fine, fine. Go ahead and publish
it. Throw it out there." Transformer,
okay, out to the world. You know, all
these projects out to the world. Sure.
And then they quit and they get venture
funding the next day and they start
their own companies. And that's the
California, you know, ecosystem. That's
the way it works. And it's very, very
good in aggregate. But Google's bled
intellectual property like no company in
history. It invented all of this stuff
that's changing the world right now.
>> Plus their 20% time which encourages
employees to go and research their their
purpose and their passions.
>> I think it's mostly a fiction at this
point. I can get hate mail from
>> but in the early days in the early days
>> in the early
>> I think the salvation for Google is
going to be the hyperscaler play just
like it is for SpaceX. Uh and yeah,
Grock 4.5, which is basically, I think
at this point, the cursor postrained off
of clawed uh reasoning traces is like
another example there. There was this
expression going around uh social media
a few weeks ago that if you can't cut it
at the frontier model level, then you
end up hyperscaling. And like that
that's the the consolation prize for for
losing the frontier model race. I think
Google is at this point finger to the
wind in terms of mandate of heaven among
the frontier labs. Google is getting the
consolation prize of being the
hyperscaler to the frontier labs.
>> Emma, do you agree with that? [snorts]
>> Yeah. I mean, look, who has the best
preference data in the world? It's
Google and it's clearly not in Gemini,
right? So, clearly it's political issues
cuz they have all the compute in the
world and others that are around that.
Um, they have got the scale though just
like why do more people use Teams than
Slack and Zoom? Like it's they have the
distributional effects. They'll still
print money. They'll still burn money.
But if you're a Google deep mind person
right now, your inbox is full, you know.
Any top person there can go out and get
a 500 million billion dollar valuation
>> and you're rich, you know, and you have
freedom and you have all the compute
probably from Google itself. So you're
like inside Google I have 100 GPUs.
Google will give me a,000 GPUs if I
leave. You know, like it's a bit of a
strange scenario you're in now. Which is
why I think Google needs to go out on
the front foot as a stock and say this
is a program we're actively doing. You
know, we're unlocking all these
geniuses. We have the biggest VC fund in
the world for this type of thing and
we're going to do exclusivity agreements
for the output that they do and they'll
be on GCP.
>> You think Google should just open
Gemini?
>> I wrote a letter to Google management 3
years ago where I said if you open
source it you will win. I think they
should ex
>> they should they're actually going to
allow um distillation from Gemini
>> major if you're if you're watching
please join us on the pod
>> and have a conversation do you open
source Gemini that would be fun
>> America needs it
>> yeah [snorts] America needs that would
be an amazing move
>> be like the Netscape Netscape to Firefox
move we like in in the era of Microsoft
we need like a top tier American open
weight model Google that
>> but I mean ultimately Google's mission
is to organize the knowledge of the
world and make it accessible and useful.
What's better than that than open source
models?
>> And remember Demis's excuse his his sort
of quasi public apology for why Gemini
itself wasn't openweight. The the claim
was we would openweight it open source
it if we had the compute but we don't
have the compute. So instead we we only
have the compute available for Gemma.
Now if that commercial argument goes
away then that argument goes away and
Google can openweight open source
Gemini.
>> Totally. You know that would be the move
of the century if they open sourced it
and they tied it to the TPUs. Yes.
>> And tied it to GCP compute and then just
built the empire on the compute. Uh that
would be the move of the
>> take over America. Yeah.
>> Yeah. And the world. That would that
would actually save the world
potentially.
>> Yeah. Uh
all right. I hope this meme gets out to
them somehow somewhere. So Google
employees, if you're if you're
listening, clip this and send it to to
Sundar and to Demis.
>> Give up the ghost and open source
Gemini, please.
>> On behalf of my Moonshot mates and
myself, I'm inviting you to join us at
our inaugural Moonshots live event on
September the 25th in downtown LA. Alex,
Salem, Dave, and I will be hosting 1,500
entrepreneurs, builders, and creators,
and hopefully you for a full day
dedicated to designing and building your
moonshot, shaping your mindset, and
steering humanity towards an abundant
future. Get ready to enjoy incredible
networking and an awesome party while
walking away with the tools to change
the future and the confidence that you
can. Seats are limited, admission is
competitive. Check it out at
moonshots.com. I'm going to move us to
some fun and big news from this week
coming from the Elon Universe. So, this
week uh Elon held SpaceX's first
earnings call. Uh and it was Vintage
Musk. The numbers were big and bigger.
Uh I listened to the earnings call. I
don't know if you guys did. I was on CNN
and CNBC commenting on the next day. Uh
I wanted to share some of the top
takeaways from the call. So, first off,
SpaceX expects to hit a h 100red billion
in annual recurring revenue by the end
of this year. And uh Elon set a target
for a trillion by 2030, maybe by 2029.
He moved up that target from 2031 to
2030, a trillion dollars of annual
revenue. Uh SpaceX posted 7.8 billion in
revenue this quarter. Uh 92%
year-over-year increase. uh he beat the
streets expectations. The company has
inked 6.7 billion in cloud service deals
in the second half of this year. Uh
SpaceX plans to hit 2 gawatts of compute
by the end of 2026 and up to 10 gawatt
by the end of 2027 and their near-term
cash engine Starlink is outperforming.
They have 12 million subscribers. That's
2x year-over-year. Uh the revenues grew
66% to 4.3 billion. I love this. Gwen
Shotwell uh also implied that Starlink's
direct satellite to mobile was going to
take a big chunk of the $600 billion
mobile telefan TAM. You know, I can't
wait to be any place on the planet in
the Gobi Desert or in the foothills of
Hollywood here and have a great cell
phone signal.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Uh yeah, it's amazing.
>> Just for context, remember no company in
world history has ever reached a
trillion dollars of revenue. just just
to
>> if anybody can you know I was on I was
on the news show saying this is the
first $10 trillion market after we start
talking about the terra fab I think it's
the first hundred trillion dollar uh
company out there um let's listen to two
quick clips from Elon and then uh
discuss them uh cuz a lot was said and
actually a lot more was said after the
earnings call a lot of news breaking out
all right first one
>> as Brett mentioned we are expecting to
reach 100 billion uh plus ARR uh in
December of this year. Um and it's it's
probably also worth mentioning that our
internal projections for reaching a
trillion dollars in revenue, not ARR but
revenue um have moved up from 2031 to
2030.
So prior to the IPO uh the financial
projections we had were reaching a
trillion dollars in in revenue uh in
2031. We now expect that to be in in
2030. Um, and uh there's a non-zero
chance of that being in 2029.
>> Uh, and then he posted uh or he said
these that got posted as clips. Let's
take a listen. I I find this really
funny and and fascinating.
>> Actually, rocket science is literally
our daily business. Um and uh you know
rocket science is a idiomatic expression
for extreme uh technological difficulty
and and there's a reason for it because
the the thing let me tell you what what
rockets desperately want to do every
flight they desperately want to blow
themselves into tiny pieces um and uh
then the engineering struggle is to u
convince the rocket not to blow itself
into tiny pieces and actually deliver
payload to orbit.
So, uh, he was making those comments
about how, uh, how hard the hard things
they're able to do and building the data
centers and building orbital compute is
nothing compared to building those
rockets. Um,
gentlemen, uh,
>> isn't it incredibly cute that Elon
doesn't know the definition of internal
projection?
>> This is a public earnings call, dude.
[laughter]
Oh, it's he's just so awesomely
transparent, isn't he? Just just
incredible.
>> So, on top of that, okay, go ahead,
Alex. I want to
>> Okay, for my nth hottake of this
episode, um I I [laughter] I think this
is not financial advice. I think the
internal now external prediction is
credible and I think there are two
possible pathways to trillion dollars in
revenue by the end of the decade. Path
one is the SpaceX Tesla merger that we
like to talk about via Optimus. So
Optimus basically takes over the the
service labor physical labor economy on
Earth and in the solar system. That's
one pathway to a trillion. Second
pathway to a trillion answers my qu the
question that I had flagged a few
episodes ago and didn't have the answer
to which is why isn't Nvidia which is so
busy commoditizing the layer above them
also commoditizing the layer below them
and I I think uh the the answer uh that
I heard from from this group at the time
was oh well like his Nvidia's
relationship with TSMC is too chummy oh
they'd never do it they're too dependent
on TSMC
I think the power move here for path
number two for SpaceX to a trillion
dollars is SpaceX replaces TSMC with the
Terapab. TSMC has almost hundred billion
a year in revenue. If you could imagine
a future where Terrafab is basically
TSMC times 10 or 20, it's American
domestic. If you roll up the values of
Micron and SKHEX and TSMC etc. So memory
plus compute plus fabulous fab and then
10x it you easily get to a tr a trillion
plus. I think the power move here is
Elon and Jensen get into bed together
and Elon becomes the new American TSMC
in deep deep partnership with Nvidia
giving Jensen the leverage he needed
against TSMC and giving Elon the path to
a trillion. And I think we're already
seeing that, right? SpaceX had already
announced a exclusive partnership with
with Nvidia. You know, I was on the
something I didn't say on the on CNBC.
Uh I think there's a lot of motivation
for Elon to drive revenues faster than
anybody could imagine. And that is to
get the valuation of SpaceX up high
enough to buy Tesla so that he's got
unquestionable control. Right now
they're on par with each other. He needs
to get the valuation up to like three
trillion and then merge in Tesla, right?
There's
>> So, Peter, sorry, just to ask you a
question on that. It's saying bad things
about Brett Adcock uh attempting to use
financial engineering to increase his
equity when Brett is doing it, but not
bad when Elon is doing it.
>> Oh, no. Because he's obviously doing it.
He's like he's like very [laughter]
clearly doing this. He's there's no
secret here, right? So, let me just So,
after the earnings call, let me hit this
one. uh and we'll we'll put more meat on
the on the table to to digest here. So
on August 4th, SpaceX and Nvidia
announced they were jointly designing
the compute payload for Star Mine. This
is uh SpaceX's orbital uh data centers.
Each Starmine satellite is going to
carry Nvidia's Reuben GPUs and Vera
CPUs. Uh and uh interestingly enough uh
and really important on the earnings
call he announced he expects to have the
first Starmine satellites in orbit in
uh a year ahead of what he was announced
earlier. So uh that's fascinating. And
then just to put more steak on the grill
here, uh the big news here uh the day
after called Reuters broke the story
that SpaceX and Tesla will initially
invest $16.8 billion to build the
terraab. Alex, we were just talking
about uh the most advanced semiconductor
complex on the planet. This is a hundred
million square foot facility. Uh it's
not a factory. This is a city. Right.
Let me just share uh this image for
everybody to see by comparison here. Um
actually let's let's hear Elon on the
Terrafab and then we'll we'll see the
images.
>> It's worth noting that there's not a
single uh high volume um computer memory
fab in America right now. Zero. Um
there's one being built in Idaho uh by
Micron, but that will not reach volume
production till I believe 2028. Um and
there's some being built in New York,
but they are in I think 29 and 30. Um
and and this is a tiny fraction of the
memory that's needed. And in fact, even
if if you take [clears throat] the best
case assumptions of the um the memory
makers and the logic makers, it is not
enough to meet the demand that is
anticipated. And that's why we need to
do the the tariff app
there will not be enough chips.
>> Yeah. Um and here if you're watching
this on YouTube, uh check this out.
Here's the terra fab. It's a mon. It's
gigantic, you know, compared to the
Pentagon, compared to Apple, compared to
the Mall of America, and compared to the
Burge Khalifa. Uh, you were saying
earlier, Alex, you know, you could
probably see this from the surface of
the moon.
>> It looks like a buckle on the planet.
Literally, if like hand of God could
reach down to this terraab structure and
grab the entire Earth by it. It's
beautiful. It's enormous. And as Elon
has now confirmed, if if you're if
you're watching this and looking at the
image, the circular structure in the
middle is, wait for it, a free electron
laser. So, not only is I I think Elon
with the Terrafab going after TSMC, he's
also going after ASML. And right now, if
you want to do extreme UV, which is the
the polite euphemism for soft X-rays
based lithography, right now you're
stuck using uh ASML's approach, which is
pretty expensive and requires creating a
vapor of of tin droplets to uh to
ultimately create those soft X-rays. By
creating a free electron laser, it's a
pretty adventurous approach to EUV
lithography. he could radically reduce
the cost and maybe even even though I've
read in in public announcements Elon
striking agreements with ASML to
purchase lots of ASML equipment. If I
were ASML uh again not financial advice,
I'd be looking at the circular structure
uh right here and saying the circular
structure is actually a bullseye painted
on ASML by Elon.
>> Oh my [laughter] god. And here's here's
the tweet. Uh this is uh he says looks
like a synchron going to build a free
electron laser based EUV machine and
Elon tweets back feltw
free electron laser for the win.
>> Yes.
>> Wow.
>> Pretty extraordinary. So
>> he's going after ASML.
>> Here's the numbers. TM TSMC invested
$330 billion to build out their fabs
over the course of 40 years. Terafab is
estimated 119 billion. It's probably a
low ball number uh but oh my god this is
the verticalization of AI uh at a level
I mean this is as you said Alex this is
the hundred trillion dollar company
>> and the Americanization like again ASML
European company TSMC Taiwanese company
Elon if this is correct he's taking that
entire stack and he's not just
verticalizing it he's onshoring it to
America for the first time in history.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Hey, uh, one thing to to add
to the party, Alex, you can confirm
this, but I did I did some Gemini based
research on this and because it didn't
make any sense to me to build a
building, a single structure that big. I
mean, I know there's ego involved and
whatever, but like why on earth? But if
you generate the X-rays or the, you
know, the EUV equivalent in that
synretron, you distribute them to all
the FAB stations throughout this one,
basically a linear accelerator
distributor. And so by being a single
structure, you only need one source of
EUV that feeds many, many manufacturing
steps across the whole building. That's
what Gemini tells me. That's
interesting. I I'm not sure of the
optics for that. How how easy it is to
like redirect X-rays that are coming off
of a circular synretron to a linear
arrangement is also just possible. I
mean, maybe Gemini knows better than I
do. It's in my mind, it's also possible.
It's just like lit literally a linear
assembly line that's coming in from both
ends or something.
>> No, I think I think tell me like we got
to research this. This is just too cool.
But you can't reflect those beams like
and move them around a building. They
can only go in a
>> X-rays are hard to create mirrors for
like X-rays really don't want to get
mirrored,
>> right? But Elon when we when we were
talking to him in December said, "Hey,
my manufacturing process, the wafers are
in these boxes.
>> You can smoke and eat a cheeseburger
over them, but they move around. So they
can move to the beam, but the beam can
only go in a straight line,
>> but it can go very, very large
distances." Hence, one long beam
projector and all these manufacturing
stations slide into the beam.
>> Maybe uh and and Alex, we talked about
this before, right? Terraab isn't just a
supply chain independence. It's
geopolitical independence. Right? If
Taiwan ever gets cut off, the company
that controls the spice, in this case,
the chip sabs
>> controls the entire AI industry. The you
could say Peter move the flops must
flow.
>> Okay. Okay. A few things here.
>> This is so cool.
>> A few things.
>> So cool.
>> A few things. One is why are we
surprised? Cuz didn't we predict this
like a while ago that this was a natural
no this was a natural outcome that we
would end up he would end up yeah full
verticalization. He'd end up building
TSM CSML something like that. He talked
about it. Right. So that's one quick
>> I think it's actually pretty surprising
like I I didn't see foresee like this
satellite map like the the big like
cremological
surprise for me is that circle like I I
did not see that circle coming and
>> how could you this is so brilliant how
could you see that coming
>> yeah I mean
>> this is like this is very related to
physics is cooked you know like the
ideas like this are going to start
popping up in all kinds of weird places
>> that that circle is profoundly
surprising Like there were like it's
funny for for years this is a a relayed
story was public information the the
Soviet Union used to stare at satellite
maps of the Pentagon and it in the
middle of the Pentagon there's this
courtyard and in the middle of the
courtyard there's this building and the
the relayed this public information the
Soviet Union was convinced that this
little building at the center of the
Pentagon was was actually like a missile
silo or had some strategic significance.
It turned out it was just a hot dog
stand. Th this is the exact [laughter]
this is the exact opposite. This is this
is a circle that has profound profound
geopolitical implications.
>> Look like if you asked me a week ago my
how often in life does something
completely change your view of the
trajectory of humanity. a week ago if
you I would have said all of you know
disassembling the moon all of the you
know the Dyson sphere it's all gated on
ASML
not being willing to more than double
their throughput of these ASML machines
that constrains chip production which
constrains the Dyson sphere which all of
that is on a SL all of a sudden all
that's out the window in just one week
>> classic Elon
>> this one circle like changes the the
geopolitics of Europe it diminishes if
this interpretation is accurate This
this one stupid little circle that
appeared in a satellite, not even an
actual satellite map, in a planned
satellite map has profound implications
for European economy, European
sovereignty, for the future of China and
Taiwan. Just one circle appearing in a
mock satellite map. [snorts]
>> I totally right. I totally agree.
>> Can I finish my point?
>> Yes, [laughter]
>> I never finished my point. Um, okay. So,
a couple things. One is the number like
the the it's really fascinating here how
hard it becomes to categorize SpaceX,
right? Is it telecoms? Is it launch like
it's like all vertically integrated and
I thought Peter your email on this that
went out to your group with the four
things was really really big. Yeah. Your
like go watch go read that. It's a big
it's a big deal. Um, I I'm I I know
everybody's super excited, but I'm kind
of like I we should we s talked about
this coming, so I don't know why
everybody's so surprised. Maybe the fact
that it's actually here and it looks
like he's actually doing it is is the
big deal, but I think we predicted this
a while ago.
>> Yeah. I mean, science fiction's
predicted a lot of things, but when it
materializes, the capital gets
commitment, you know, the partnerships
get announced,
>> you know, and and while Elon's probably
never right on his timelines, he always
implements the idea eventually, and it's
exciting. [laughter]
>> 10x everything on a quarterly.
>> Also, to your point, like I I think
there's like there's a physics surprise
here. It it seems that he's confirmed
the circle is a free electron laser.
He's not using tin droplets to do EUV.
That's a that's like a a technological
surprise. That isn't just like, oh, Elon
is out buying ASML machines or
contracting with TSMC or Samsung.
Whatever happened to Samsung?
He's he's off like doing his own thing,
not just by taking the existing supply
chain and putting it under one roof.
There's new physics.
>> Yeah, he's he's leaprogging. Well, I
think that the way to think about
>> analogy
>> email the way to think about SpaceX is
it's the vehicle for the intelligence
industrialization of America, right?
Like [snorts] ultimately you need to
build a brand new capital stock from
rockets to chips to robots and Elon's
got the financial arbitrage and the
talent arbitrage and the selling point
now to bring that all together. So
everything that will be economically
productive in this next century,
Elon's going full stack on. That's the
fundamental thing. And the spending on
that, the trillion dollars we've had in
AI chips is just the first stage.
Because if you think about the spending
that America and the rest of the world
has to do over the next few decades,
what is it? Robots, rockets,
chips. And so that is his story. It's
the industrialization of America for the
intelligence age. he will be the company
that does that with the capital in terms
of human and financial edge that's
required to do that.
>> I'll also point out one more thing which
is now that we know what a terra fab on
earth looks like. It's not difficult to
take that same top down view and imagine
what one of these on the moon looks like
and you know what else would benefit
from that high aspect ratio dimension
a mass driver.
>> Yes. So I looked at that and I saw, oh
my goodness, not just the circle in the
middle, which is provocative and speaks
volumes about the future of European
economic sovereignty, but also the high
aspect ratio length. And I saw, oh my
goodness, this looks like it could be a
mass driver on the moon.
I think as well as you get through the
economic downturn that's going to come
as human cognitive labor goes negative
you have to know the US government's
going to go balls to the wall with
infrastructure spending and things like
this will absorb that in easily
multiples of them
>> yeah you know there was a comment made
someone made before which is buy SpaceX
stock for your children and again not
investment advice but this is a
generational company uh it's a
civilizational infrastructure company.
Uh it was nice to see the stock uh you
know couple days ago 20% of the stock
float became available for a lot of
people including myself and very few
sold. In fact the price has gone up over
the last few days. A lot of belief in
where it's going. Gentlemen
>> full disclo full disclosure I'm now a
small SpaceX shareholder.
>> Yes. Well it's my single largest
holding. So and I'm going to be holding
you know the old hodddle for Bitcoin.
Huddle your SpaceX.
[laughter]
Gentlemen, a pleasure. Uh, Immod, thank
you for joining us today. Uh, always
always a pleasure. And, uh, guys, uh, I
loved the episode.
>> Oh, God. Learned so much. Always learned
so much. But it drives me crazy that I
have to go listen to each one again just
to understand and fully digest
[laughter] what we talked about. But it,
but you have to. You have to.
>> Oh, love you guys.